<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning given to secure sinners to prepare for judgement, to flee from wrath to come, and turn from all sin but especially the sin which does most easily beset them / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12705279</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12705279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 371:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning given to secure sinners to prepare for judgement, to flee from wrath to come, and turn from all sin but especially the sin which does most easily beset them / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 41-44 are tightly bound in filmed copy. Pages 28-59 photographed from Union Theological Seminary Library, New York copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING GIVEN TO Secure Sinners, TO Prepare for <hi>Judgment,</hi> TO Flee from <hi>Wrath to Come,</hi> AND Turn from <hi>All Sin;</hi> BUT Eſpecially the Sin which does <hi>moſt eaſily beſet them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL VINCENT,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezek. 33. 7.</bibl> 
               <hi>O Son of Man, I have ſet thee a Watchman unto the houſe of Iſrael, therefore thou ſhalt hear the Word at my Mouth, and warn them from Me.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>LICENSED,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>March</hi> 17th. 1688.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>three Crowns,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66016:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66016:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>WHen I Preached theſe following Sermons, I had not the leaſt thought of Publiſhing them: They were taken from my Mouth by a dexterous and nimble hand that wrote almoſt every Word I utter'd: I was very much ſollicited to Print them; and the Notes being written out fair, and brought to me, I have look'd them over, and now they are preſented to thee, with a ſincere Deſign that they</hi> may be <hi>beneficial to thee, and not without Hope</hi> they will be ſo. <hi>The Subjects here handled are</hi> awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening; <hi>and in this</hi> ſecure Age, <hi>what need is there of</hi> ſtartling Sermons! <hi>At this day in</hi> England, <hi>there is work enough for many a</hi> Boanerges, <hi>for</hi> ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Sons of Thunder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The guilt and defilement of Sin, proves it to be Mans greateſt Enemy; but becauſe it ſtupifies and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens thoſe that have been guilty of it, it is likely the more effectually to deſtroy them; for the</hi> Diſeaſe <hi>not being</hi> felt, <hi>the</hi> Remedy <hi>is</hi> neglected. <hi>A ſpiritual Lethargy is the general Diſtemper, moſt continue</hi> faſt aſleep in Sin, <hi>till</hi> Hell wakes them, <hi>but then it is</hi> too late. <hi>Though Chriſt has the</hi> Key of Hell, <hi>that Saviour</hi> releaſes none <hi>that once are thrown into it.</hi> Miſerable World, becauſe it lies in Wickedneſs! more <hi>miſerable, becauſe it apprehends not</hi> how <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable its Wickedneſs has made it! becauſe it</hi> fears not, <hi>it</hi> endeavours <hi>not to</hi> eſcape Eternal Miſery!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh</hi> dreadful Day of God <hi>that's coming! when all Apoſtate Angels that are now</hi> in Chains of Darkneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:66016:3"/> 
               <hi>ſhall be brought forth and judged,</hi> and dealt <hi>with as the Enemtes of God and Man: Theſe Principalities and Powers will be overpowr'd, and utterly unable to avoid the ſeverity of their Righteous and Almighty Judge: How much evil have they done, and ſtill they are doing more! of what</hi> Woe and Torment <hi>are they</hi> capable!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all thoſe of the Children of Men who have been</hi> led Captive by Satan at his Pleaſure, <hi>that have reſolved rather to be</hi> deſtroyed themſelves, <hi>than that the</hi> works of the Devil ſhould be deſtroyed in them, <hi>'tis</hi> juſt <hi>that they</hi> ſhould, <hi>but how</hi> ſad <hi>will it be for them, to</hi> ſhare in Torment <hi>with him! Sin will have a very bad end; all that are gone into</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, <hi>are ſenſible of</hi> it, <hi>though</hi> few <hi>in</hi> this <hi>World perceive it. When the Servants of Sin have received their</hi> Wages, <hi>which is</hi> Death; <hi>then they will know to their ſorrow,</hi> what kind of Maſter <hi>they have ſerved, and what</hi> Pains <hi>they fooliſhly took</hi> for <hi>that</hi> Miſery, <hi>which they ſhould have taken Pains</hi> to have prevented.</p>
            <p>Reader!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be wiſe, believe and fear, and</hi> take the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Warning: <hi>The Sword in the</hi> Hand <hi>of the</hi> living Eternal God <hi>will give a</hi> dreadful <hi>and a</hi> deadly Blow; <hi>to fall under his Vengeance will be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and</hi> thy Blood lying upon thy own Head, <hi>it will lye</hi> very heavy, <hi>and upon this will follow ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting heavines and anguiſh. Oh fear the</hi> Wrath to come before 'tis come, <hi>and fly from</hi> Sin, <hi>nnd</hi> come to God by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>a Saviour both from</hi> Sin <hi>and</hi> Wrath, <hi>and a Saviour to the</hi> uttermoſt. <hi>Better Counſel than</hi> this <hi>cannot be</hi> taken <hi>by thy ſelf, or</hi> given <hi>by any to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66016:3"/>ROM. XIV. 10. latter part.</bibl>
               <q>—We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have been lately Diſcourſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Converſion:</hi> The Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I make this day, is ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to my great Deſign, which is the Converſion and Salvation of this Aſſembly: It infinitely concerns you all to turn to God, for quickly you will have a <hi>Summons</hi> to come unto <hi>his Bar,</hi> and how ſoon that Summons may be given, who can tell? Thoſe that <hi>leaſt think on't,</hi> and leaſt care to be <hi>provided and ready for</hi> it, perhaps may have it ſooneſt; and if the Converts themſelves, as the Scripture tells us, are <hi>ſcarcely ſaved;</hi> Oh where ſhall the Unconverted and <hi>the Sinner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear?</hi> I wiſh that <hi>I may Preach</hi> and <hi>you may Hear,</hi> as thoſe who do really believe <hi>we ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment ſeat of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in theſe words ſpeaks enough, one would think, to ſtartle the moſt ſtupid Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to make the moſt ſecure, like <hi>Felix</hi> to tremble; to awaken even thoſe that are dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes. Let me tell you, the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils themſelves</hi> are <hi>none</hi> of them <hi>Atheiſts and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66016:4"/> they all believe this Text, and the thoughts of Judgment make <hi>them tremble;</hi> therefore if any Sinner remains fearleſs and unſenſible, he does in this reſpect <hi>out ſin</hi> the very <hi>Apoſtate Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three things obſervable in the Words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is a <hi>Judgment Seat,</hi> the moſt <hi>glorious</hi> that ever <hi>was,</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> that ever will be; from this <hi>Tribunal</hi> there can be <hi>no Appeal</hi> unto any other, the Sentence whether of <hi>Abſolution</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> that will here be paſs't, will <hi>never be revers'd,</hi> but ſtand firm unto Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You are told <hi>who</hi> is to be the <hi>Judge,</hi> he is the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> We read of a twofold Appearing of Chriſt, his <hi>firſt</hi> and his <hi>ſecond</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: He came at firſt in the <hi>form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> he was <hi>to be</hi> made Sin, and he <hi>was made Sin and a Curſe</hi> for us: He <hi>gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all Iniquity;</hi> and if he had given <hi>other and leſs</hi> than <hi>himſelf,</hi> it would not have ſatisfied. The Churches Sins could be done away by no <hi>lower a Prieſt,</hi> than Chriſt the <hi>greateſt</hi> and <hi>higheſt</hi> of all; and the Prieſt was ſain <hi>himſelf</hi> to be, and that a <hi>moſt voluntary Sacrifice.</hi> He appear'd at firſt to <hi>put away ſin by the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of himſelf;</hi> but when he comes the ſecond time, to Judge the World, he will appear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another kind of manner: From the <hi>beginning</hi> of the World, there hath not been <hi>ſuch a ſight</hi> as there <hi>will be</hi> at the <hi>end of it.</hi> The Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will come with a <hi>Power</hi> which none can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, with <hi>great Glory,</hi> which will fill the Saints with Joy; for they <hi>ſhall appear in glory with him,</hi> but will be exceedingly amazing and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all thoſe who were the Enemies of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66016:4"/>3. Here are the <hi>Perſons</hi> that are to <hi>ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> this Judge; if you ask, <hi>Who are they?</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by another Queſtion, <hi>Who, or where are the Perſons that ſhall be exempted? All</hi> from the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> of the World to the <hi>end</hi> of it, <hi>All</hi> from the <hi>firſt Man</hi> that was made, unto the <hi>last</hi> of his Poſterity that ſhall be born, muſt ſtand before Chriſt the Lord, that from his Mouth they may receive their final and eternal Doom. There is a great difference between <hi>ſtanding before the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat,</hi> and <hi>standing in Judgment;</hi> the <hi>former</hi> implies being <hi>made to appear</hi> at the Tribunal, the <hi>latter</hi> implies being <hi>Acquitted</hi> there. The Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt tells us, That <hi>the ungodly ſhall not ſtand in the Judgment, nor Sinners in the Congregation of the Righteous,</hi> Pſal. 1. 5. yet all of theſe ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to appear at the Bar of God, there they ſhall ſtand trembling, expecting the terrible Sentence of Condemnation: And Oh what a <hi>hideous Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry</hi> will the <hi>whole multitude</hi> of Wicked and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Ones make, when without <hi>hope of Mercy</hi> they are adjudged to <hi>endleſs Miſery!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The Doctrine I raiſe from the Words is this, <hi>All ſhall be Judged by Chriſt at the great Day:</hi> As certainly as you are all here, ſo certainly at that day you ſhall appear at his Judgment Seat. Death is not <hi>more</hi> certain, nay, 'tis not <hi>ſo</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as Judgment. The Apoſtle tells us that, <hi>all ſhall not Dye,</hi> for ſome ſhall be <hi>Changed;</hi> but even theſe that are changed, though they <hi>ſcape the Grave,</hi> they ſhall <hi>ſtand at the Tribunal,</hi> and <hi>give account of themſelves unto God.</hi> This Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Judgment, was Preached early in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66016:5"/> World; we find 'twas Publiſhed before the Flood of <hi>Noah,</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>Jude</hi> v. 14, 15. where you have the ſumme of a Sermon, but a very ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible one, Preached by <hi>Enoch</hi> the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from <hi>Adam; Behold the Lord cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints, to execute Judgment upon all; and to convince all that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all the hard ſpeeches which ungodly Sinners have ſpoken againſt him.</hi> Under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> heard the ſame Doctrine: That great Prince and Preacher <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> thus concludes his Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſplayed the Creatures <hi>Vanity,</hi> having taught Man his Intereſt and Duty, <hi>To fear God, and to keep his commandments;</hi> he cloſes with theſe words, <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> ult. <hi>God will bring every work in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil:</hi> And how plainly does the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>2 Cor. 5. 10, 11. For we muſt all appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Christ, that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad; knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we perſwade Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Doctrine, this is the Method I ſhall obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Him</hi> that is to be the <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak concerning the <hi>Perſons</hi> that are to be <hi>judged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Concerning the <hi>things</hi> that ſhall be <hi>brought into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate the <hi>Certainty</hi> of this Judgmont<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66016:5"/>
            <p>And then in the laſt Place make <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Place I am to Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Judge,</hi> and the Text plainly tells us, that the Judge is <hi>Chriſt:</hi> The <hi>Father</hi> I grant, is ſaid to judge, <hi>1 Pet. 1. 17. If ye call on the Father, who without reſpect of perſons judgeth according to every mans work, paſs the time of your ſojourning here in fear:</hi> Yet it is ſaid in another place, <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgeth no man, but hath committed all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son,</hi> Joh. 5. 22. How ſhall theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be reconciled? The reconciliation is eaſie, thus; the Father judges, becauſe the <hi>Authority of Judging</hi> belongs to him, becauſe he does <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto the Sons Judgment,</hi> and has ordained him to Judge the World in Righteouſneſs; the truth is, the Father Judges all, but 'tis <hi>mediately</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt: And yet in another ſenſe the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judges not,</hi> becauſe Chriſt the Son, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon in the Godhead <hi>alone, was incarnate</hi> and manifeſted in the Fleſh, and He alone will <hi>viſibly Judge</hi> the World at the great approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day.</p>
            <p>Theſe four things may be obſerved concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt the Judge.</p>
            <p>He is a <hi>Saviour to the uttermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is the <hi>Only Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is <hi>Lord of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>ſuch a Lord,</hi> he will come with <hi>a moſt glorious Attendance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt the Judge is a <hi>Saviour to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,</hi> and really at the Judgment-day he will <hi>compleat</hi> the Churches <hi>Salvation;</hi> he began it here in this World, and ſtill is carrying it on; but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66016:6"/> the laſt day will be the day, in which he will put his <hi>laſt Hand</hi> to this Work, and make it <hi>perfect,</hi> Heb. 9. 28. <hi>Chriſt was once offered up to bear the ſins of many, and unto them that look for him ſhall he appear the ſecond time, without ſin to Salvation;</hi> then Salvation ſhall be conſummate, the whole of it ſhall be wrought, nothing of Sin or the ſad effects of it ſhall remain, nothing that ſhall cauſe the leaſt frown in the Face of God to eternity: Death will be ſwallowed up in Victory, the whole Man will be glorious and immortal; Chriſt will then have compleated his whole Deſign upon all his Saints and Members, he will have made them as holy and happy as he did intend to make them, he will indeed <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Church a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but it ſhall be</hi> all <hi>holy,</hi> and its Beauty without the leaſt <hi>blemiſh, Eph. 5. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt the Judge is the <hi>Only Saviour,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that are <hi>Condemn'd</hi> by <hi>Him,</hi> 'tis in vain for them to expect Salvation from <hi>any other:</hi> Chriſt is the <hi>only Foundation-ſtone</hi> on which all that build ſhall ſtand; other Builders are fooliſh, and build upon the <hi>ſand,</hi> and what they build will fall, and <hi>great will be the fall of it.</hi> They that are not interſted in the Lord Jeſus by Faith, that are not Juſtified by his Blood, who beſides can ſave them from Wrath? thoſe whoſe Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are not done away by his offering up of himſelf without ſpot to God, there can be found no other <hi>Sacrifice for their ſins,</hi> but a <hi>certain fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful looking for of Judgment, and fiery indignation that ſhall devour the Adverſaries:</hi> And how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66016:6"/> will it be to be Sentenced to Death and Damnation, by the only Author of Salvation and Life! they that by his Mouth ſhall be doom'd to eternal Deſtruction, that Deſtruction will be made ten thouſand times the <hi>ſorer</hi> by <hi>eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation:</hi> Alas, what Hope can be left, when the Lamb of God, who alone <hi>can take away Sin,</hi> ſhall be ſo full of Wrath, as for ever reject and caſt away the Sinner?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt the Judge is <hi>Lord of all;</hi> this is a truth that the Tongue of an Angel did Proclaim, <hi>Luk. 2. 11.</hi> a truth that <hi>every Tongue ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,</hi> Phil. 2. 11. that <hi>every Heart</hi> ought to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> and which the moſt <hi>unbelieving</hi> and <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> at laſt ſhall be <hi>made to know.</hi> Chriſt hath on his <hi>Veſture, and on his Thigh, this Name written, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> Rev. 19. 16. He has all Power in his hand, things in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Earth, and under the Earth are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him: Thoſe that are wiſe do willingly how before him, and they who will not bow, he can eaſily break and daſh them to pieces. A mighty Lord Chriſt is, at whoſe Command <hi>Death</hi> ſhall <hi>deliver again all</hi> that for ſo many years he had <hi>impriſoned</hi> in the <hi>Grave;</hi> he has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Key of Death and Hell too, <hi>Rev. 1. 18.</hi> both are under his Power; at his Command al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the Earth alſo and the works therein ſhall be burnt up:</hi> There is no dealing with this Judge by way of <hi>reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> it concerns us all to be <hi>diligent, that we may be found of him in peace, without ſpot and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 10, 14.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66016:7"/>4. Chriſt the Judge will come with a <hi>most glorious Attendance:</hi> How awakening to the World will the <hi>Voice of the Arch-Angel and the Trump of God</hi> be! Chriſt will appear with a light far above the brightneſs of the Sun, not a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his but ſhall ſhine like that glorious Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary, <hi>Mat. 13. 43. Then ſhall the righteous ſhine as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father:</hi> And what a ſpectacle will all the Saints together be, as ſo many millions of Suns ſhining at <hi>Once,</hi> and their Lord in the heighth of Glory at the head of them! He will be revealed alſo with his <hi>mighty Angels;</hi> theſe excellent Spirits at his Command, <hi>ministred</hi> unto his <hi>Members</hi> on Earth, and they will wait upon the <hi>Head</hi> at the day of his <hi>appearing and his Kingdom.</hi> There is much Work for the Angels to do at the Worlds end, they are compared to <hi>Reapers</hi> that are ſafely to <hi>gather the Wheat,</hi> and to bind the <hi>Tares in bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles</hi> for the <hi>fire, Mat. 13. 41, 42. The Son of Man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniquity, and ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire; there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> The greateſt Train of Nobility and Courtiers that attend at the Coronation of the higheſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour on Earth, are but a <hi>poor ſhew</hi> to an <hi>innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Company of Angels;</hi> for <hi>all in Heaven</hi> will be with Chriſt at Judgment, to do him honour who is indeed the <hi>Head of all Principality and Power.</hi> Thus of the <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond Place I am to ſpeak of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are to be judged:</hi> The Text takes in <hi>All</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66016:7"/> therefore none ſhall be exempted, and none in a vain and fooliſh imagination ſhould exempt themſelves: It will be a <hi>general Aſſize,</hi> at which all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>higheſt and greateſt of Men will be brought to Judgment:</hi> Death makes bold with <hi>them</hi> as well as others, and enters the ſtatelieſt Palaces, the ſtrongeſt Forts, as well as the Cottages of the meaneſt. The Rulers and Conquerors of the World, that <hi>cauſed Terror in the land of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> yet they are made to <hi>bear the ſhame</hi> of their <hi>Weakneſs and Mortality;</hi> they are <hi>brought down to the Pit,</hi> their <hi>Swords are laid under their Heads,</hi> their <hi>Hands</hi> being able to <hi>hold them no longer, Ezek. 32. 27.</hi> And if Death is not afraid to <hi>ſeize them,</hi> ſurely <hi>Chriſt will not be afraid to Judge them.</hi> This mighty Lord <hi>regards not the perſons of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor the rich more than the poor;</hi> Job 34. 19. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> ſpeaking to the great Ones of the World, <hi>but ye ſhall dye like Men, Pſal. 82. 7.</hi> Princes are <hi>greater</hi> Worms, other Men are <hi>leſſer,</hi> but all muſt call <hi>Corruption Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and when they come to ſtand before Chriſts bar, foregoing earthly Dignity will be inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, all muſt ſtand upon even ground: And truly thoſe great Ones of the World that have abuſed their Power, and by a bad example drawn many to Sin and to Hell after them, their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will but Increaſe their Account and Miſery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the greateſt, ſo the <hi>Meaneſt muſt be brought to Judgment,</hi> though there is never ſo vaſt a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; God takes notice of them all <hi>now,</hi> and none of them muſt think to ofcape in a crowd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66016:8"/> 
               <hi>then:</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks plainly of Individuals, <hi>Rom. 14. 12. So then every one of us ſhall give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of himſelf to God:</hi> Thoſe that live moſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and retired, are under Gods continual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection; they that are of the loweſt rank and quality, whom, there are that diſdain ſo much as to look upon, yet God ſees them. The Sun ſhines upon a Mole-hill as well as upon a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, upon a Shrub as well as upon a Cedar, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Fly as well as upon an Emperor; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the All-ſeeing Eye of God beholds the <hi>low</hi> as well as the <hi>high,</hi> and there is not any one of them all, but ſhall be made to render an account of all his doings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Righteous <hi>Ones muſt ſtand before Chriſts Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat:</hi> All his <hi>Members</hi> muſt appear before <hi>Him</hi> their <hi>Head,</hi> but ſhall be dealt with after a <hi>different manner</hi> from others; <hi>Grace and Love</hi> makes a <hi>difference</hi> now, but how highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied will the Grace of Chriſt be in the <hi>difference it makes at that Day?</hi> to find <hi>Mercy of the Lord in that day,</hi> which the Apoſtle Prays <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> might find, <hi>2 Tim. 1. 18.</hi> when the greateſt part of the World ſhall with a ſtrong hand, the Ear being deaf to all their cryes, be turned into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire; this is <hi>great Mercy</hi> indeed, great as <hi>the Heaven is high above the Earth.</hi> The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall appear, but they ſhall be ſet at their <hi>Lords right hand,</hi> to ſhew his peculiar Favour to them, and they ſhall joyfully own what that Hand has done for them. Chriſts Appearing will be glorious, and ſo will be the appearing of his Saints; then 'twill be underſtood what 'tis to be a Saint, <hi>Col. 3. 4. When Chriſt who is our life
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66016:8"/> ſhall appear, than ſhall ye alſo appear with him in Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Queſtion is here ſtarted by ſome, <hi>Whether the Sins of the Righteous ſhall be then made known?</hi> The Scripture plainly tells us, That when the Sins of ſuch <hi>come to be ſought for, there ſhall be none,</hi> and <hi>that they ſhall not be found;</hi> none of them ſhall be <hi>imputed</hi> or <hi>laid to their charge,</hi> none ſhall be <hi>ſo diſcover'd</hi> in Judgment, as to <hi>riſe up</hi> in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, to Condemn them: But ſince there will ſuch a light ſhine at that day that will make all things manifeſt, both good and evil, ſuppoſe the Iniquities of the Righteous ſhould be made known to the whole Creation, ſuch will be their Purity, ſuch will be their Bleſſedneſs and Joy, that there will not be the <hi>leaſt room for ſhame or ſorrow</hi> at the diſcovery: But when all the Sins that have been Forgiven and Purged, ſhall be revealed, others as well as themſelves will be filled with <hi>Wonder at the Blood of Jeſus,</hi> and the <hi>powerful Grace of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As the Righteous, ſo <hi>the Wicked muſt stand before Christs Bar;</hi> they would fain not come thither, but there is an irreſiſtible Power to force them. The Malefactor who is Condemned for Murther, Rape, or Treaſon, would fain decline the Judges View, he is Self-condemn'd, and therefore fears the Judges Sentence; but the Gaoler, the Officers compel him to the Bar, where Judgment is given againſt him to take away his Life. Wicked Men will be horribly afraid to make their Appearance before the Lord Jeſus, whoſe Salvation they have flighted, whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om and Government they would by no means
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66016:9"/> ſubmit unto; they will wiſh that their <hi>Bodies might ſleep eternally</hi> in their Graves, and never have ſuch a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> which will be <hi>only to Damnation;</hi> they will wiſh rather to be turned into <hi>Nothing,</hi> than to be turned into <hi>Hell;</hi> they will <hi>call to the Rocks and the Mountains to fall upon them, to hide them from the Face of him that ſits upon the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb, Rev. 6. 16.</hi> But will they, nill they, they muſt appear at his Seat, and ſee him Eye to Eye, though his Eye will be as a flame of Fire to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie them: That juſt Indignation that ſparkles from Chriſts looks, how will it amaze them! <hi>Rev. 1. 7. Behold he cometh with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and all the kindreds of the earth ſhall wail becauſe of him, even ſo Amen;</hi> the thing is certain.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They that <hi>never heard Christs Goſpel ſhall be brought to Judgment:</hi> He is to Judge the Church, and the whole World in Righteouſneſs. The State of thoſe that are without the Goſpel, is ſet forth as very ſad in Scripture; they are ſaid to be <hi>without Christ, being aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers to the Covenants of Promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the World,</hi> Eph. 2. 12. Yet it ſeems to me an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable boldneſs, to pronounce them <hi>all loſt;</hi> ſince for ought we know, God may help ſome of them to <hi>be faithful in that little</hi> he has given them; but however, be it, or be it not ſo, their Caſe is ſo dangerous, that we ſhould be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very much for them at preſent, and Pray that God would make <hi>known his ſaving health</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. The Apoſtle tells us, what will be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66016:9"/> the Rule of Chriſt's proceedings with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that never heard of the glad-tydings of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; they ſhall be <hi>judged according to the Law and Light of Nature,</hi> Rom. 2. 12. <hi>As many as have ſinned without Law, ſhall alſo periſh without Law, and as many as have ſinned in the Law, ſhall be judged by the Law; for not the hearers of the Law are juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. They that have <hi>enjoyed the Goſpel, and the means of Grace, ſhall be brought to Judgment;</hi> and of all perſons that are to be judged, <hi>theſe</hi> have <hi>largest account</hi> to give; and the <hi>most Talents</hi> to anſwer for. A poor Heathen, he has but one Talent, the dim Light of nature; but thou that enjoyeſt the Goſpel, haſt <hi>two,</hi> if not <hi>five</hi> Talents to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove: And where much is given, will not much alſo be required; you that hear Chriſt Preached, had need to look to it, that you ſincerely obey him now; and that you may ſtand before him at laſt; for if you fall in Judgment, you will fall very low. Damnation will be great and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, where <hi>great Salvation</hi> has been <hi>neglected, Heb. 2. 3.</hi> Our Lord Jeſus plainly intimates, that there are degrees of Torment in the place of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture puniſhment; there is a blacker Darkneſs, and a Darkneſs not quite ſo dima: there is a <hi>cooler</hi> and an <hi>hotter</hi> Hell. Who are thoſe that ſhall be thrown into the hotteſt Hell of all? Truly thoſe who heard the Goſpel, and were called to repent and believe; but would do neither, <hi>Mat. 11. 21, 22, 23, 24. Woe unto thee</hi> Chorazin, <hi>woe unto thee</hi> Bethſaida, <hi>for if the mighty works that were done in you, had been done in</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon, <hi>they would have Repented long ago in Sack-cloath and Aſlies: but I ſay
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66016:10"/> to you, it ſhall be more tolerable for</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon <hi>in the day of Judgment, than for you. And thou</hi> Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum, <hi>that art exalted unto Heaven, ſhalt be caſt down to Hell; for if the mighty works which have been done in thee, had been done in</hi> Sodom, <hi>it would have remained to this day. But I ſay to you, it ſhall be more tolerable for the Land of</hi> Sodom <hi>in the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than for Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, I am to ſpeak of the things which will be brought into Judgment, and that both with reſpect to the <hi>Righteous,</hi> and with reſpect to the <hi>Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the Righteous; and concerning theſe you muſt know,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Sincerity</hi> at the day of Judgment, will be <hi>made apparent.</hi> All the Sincerity that has been on Earth, will then be own'd and approved; every one ſhall have an <hi>Euge,</hi> a Commendation, that has been <hi>a good and faithful Servant,</hi> Mat. 25. 21, 23. The Apoſtle prays for the <hi>Philippians, Ch. 1. 10.</hi> that they <hi>might be Sincere, and without offence till the day of Chriſt.</hi> Sincerity will ſignifie much in that Day: None will paſs for ſincere, but thoſe that are ſo. Not one that has been ſincere, but ſhall be accepted and rewarded. Faithful ones may now poſſibly he loaded with Reproaches from without; and with Cenſures from within the Church; but at the great Day, all will be wiped off, <hi>1 Cor. 4. 5. Judge nothing before the time, until the Lord do come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and make manifeſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Hearts, and then ſhall every Man have praiſe of God.</hi> How many that have been <hi>highly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66016:10"/> eſteemed among Men,</hi> will be diſcovered then to have been <hi>unſound at Heart;</hi> and that the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Self</hi> did <hi>act</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> them; tho their Tongues did ſpeak for <hi>God,</hi> and tho they made a <hi>Splendid Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that they were <hi>his Servants.</hi> And how many that have been hardly thought of by Men, will Chriſt at that day <hi>confeſs before his Father and the Angels?</hi> their Cenſurers at the ſame time being aſhamed and confounded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There will <hi>Cognizance be taken of all the good works of the Righteous.</hi> Theſe will <hi>follow them into another World,</hi> Rev. 14. 13. The Apoſtle, that he might encourage Believers unto diligence, tells them, <hi>Heb. 6. 10. God is not unrighteous to forget your Work and Labour of love, which ye have ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Name.</hi> Good works are <hi>rewardable,</hi> tho they are not <hi>Meritorious:</hi> there is no proportion between the work and the reward, but the reward infinitely exceeds, for <hi>God himſelf</hi> is the <hi>reward</hi> of the Saints, and <hi>All in all</hi> that are in Heaven. There is no intrinſick worth in good works to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Heaven; but God has promiſed Heaven and eternal Life, and is Righteous in beſtowing it; but ſtill it muſt be acknowledged his free Gift, and <hi>given through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Indeed, <hi>Mat. 25. 35, 40. mention</hi> is made only of works of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Mercy. <hi>I was an Hungred, and ye gave me Meat, Thirſty and ye gave me Drink, I was a Stranger, and ye took me in. I was Naked, and ye cloathed me; Sick, and ye viſited me. I was in Priſon, and ye came to me.</hi> From hence you are to learn how acceptable ſuch works as theſe are; and you ſhould be ſtirr'd up to abound in them; but <hi>other works</hi> are <hi>not excluded;</hi> for afterwards our Lord
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66016:11"/> does <hi>only mention</hi> the <hi>mercileſneſs,</hi> and <hi>uncharitable Omiſſions</hi> of the wicked; and yet 'tis plain from other Scriptures, that their <hi>other Sins</hi> will be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; their not <hi>knowing God,</hi> their <hi>diſobedience to the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1. 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Sentence which will be paſt upon them, will be a <hi>Sentence of Abſolution:</hi> they ſhall be abſolved and acquitted openly before Men and Angels. All their Sins will be forgotten, and buried; there will be an eternal deliverance from the Curſe. With what Admiration, Joy and Triumph will they hear, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, from the Foundation of the World!</hi> Mat. 25. 34. What a Kingdom is that, that never ſhall be moved! What a Crown is that, that is incorruptible! What gladneſs will fill their Hearts, when the Crown of Life is put upon their Heads! The Sentence being pronounced, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently 'twill be done according to this Sentence; poſſeſſion will be taken of the glorious Inheritance, they ſhall <hi>enter into life Eternal,</hi> Mat. 25. 46. Thus of the Righteous.</p>
            <p>I am to ſpeak alſo concerning the Wicked; and as to theſe, you muſt underſtand,</p>
            <p n="1">1. All the <hi>works of wicked men will be brought into Judgment.</hi> All their ſinful Deeds will follow them to the Bar of God! they will riſe with them, and againſt them at that Day: when a Sinner ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and all his Drunkenneſs, his Whoredoms, his unjuſt and cheating Actions, all his evil Deeds of every fort, ſhall <hi>ſurround and appear with him,</hi> before the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Righteous Judge!</hi> How will he be amazed at the <hi>ſight</hi> of all his Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! How will he tremble to <hi>hear</hi> how <hi>loud they cry
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66016:11"/> for Vengeance upon him!</hi> Not a deed of Darkneſs, but then will be brought to light, to his greater confuſion!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not only the <hi>Works</hi> of the Wicked, but their <hi>very Words ſhall all be accounted for.</hi> The Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſpeaks this very plainly, <hi>Mat. 12. 36. But I ſay unto you, that every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give an account thereof in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> By <hi>idle</hi> words may be meant words uſeleſs and unprofitable to the Speakers and to the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or <hi>idle</hi> and <hi>vain,</hi> according to the Hebrew uſe, may ſignifie, <hi>falſe, deceitful, lying.</hi> God does hear all words at preſent, <hi>Pſal. 139. 4. There is not a word in my Tongue, but lo, O Lord, thou knoweſt it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together.</hi> And words which very much declare what moſt abounds in the Heart, muſt be anſweerd for at laſt. And if unprofitable talk will then be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, how ſad will be the Caſe of all obſcene and filthy Speakers! of all egregious Lyars! of all injurious Slanderers and Back-biters! of all Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, curſing curſed Swearers! of all whoſe impious Tongues have made bold with the <hi>Blood and Wounds</hi> of God their Judge, and inſtead of ſerious praying, have moſt preſumptuouſly <hi>called upon,</hi> and <hi>dared God</hi> to <hi>Damn them!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As the works and words, ſo <hi>the Thoughts of wicked men</hi> ſhall be brought into Judgment. Thoughts are Sins, and need forgiveneſs; and ought to be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of. Memorable is that which <hi>Simon Peter</hi> ſays to <hi>Simon Magus, Act. 8. 22. Repent therefore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy Heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> If theſe are not repented of and pardon'd, alas, theſe alſo muſt be charged upon Sinners; vaſtly to the increaſing of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66016:12"/> their puniſhment. How innumerable are the Thouſands of thouſands, the Millions of Millions of vain and wicked thoughts, deſires and luſtings that have lodged in the Hearts of the ungodly! The heart ſearcher ſees every one of them; and will make them know at the laſt day, that he remembers all. Proud and Self-conceited Thoughts, and touring imaginations; impure and laſcivious Thoughts, and inward boyling of Concupiſcence; inſatiable Covetouſneſs, and eager projects for <hi>filthy gain;</hi> the ſtirrings of Envy, Malice, Anger and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; the Judge will take notice of all; for <hi>he knows what is in Man,</hi> Joh. 2. 25. It will be a <hi>large Bill of Inditement,</hi> where Deeds, Words and Thoughts are all written down from firſt to laſt, and not ſo much as <hi>one</hi> forgotten. The opening of the <hi>Book of Gods remembrance</hi> where all are recorded, will be very amazing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Sentence that will be paſt upon the wicked, will be unconceivably full of horrour,</hi> Mat. 25. 41. <hi>Then ſhall he ſay to them on the Left-hand, Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> For <hi>Him,</hi> who is the <hi>way to come</hi> to God, to ſay <hi>Depart!</hi> to God, to ſay <hi>Depart!</hi> to depart from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Sinners <hi>only Hope and Saviour!</hi> to depart with a <hi>Curſe!</hi> to depart into <hi>Fire,</hi> the Extremity of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! to depart into <hi>everlaſting Fire!</hi> to be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented without any intermiſſion or end! to be for ever in ſuch evil and hateful Company, as <hi>Devils and damned Angels!</hi> this is woful beyond all utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance! And this Sentence as ſoon as paſs'd, will be put in Execution. <hi>Now</hi> indeed, ſuch is the patience of God, <hi>Sentence againſt an evil work is not ſpeedily Executed; and therefore ſuch is their Maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66016:12"/> and Ingratitude, <hi>the Heart of the Sons of men is fully ſet in them to do Evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 11. But at the great day, as ſoon as the wicked are Sentenced, they will be ſent, and forced to go away <hi>into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Puniſhment,</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>ult.</hi> the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>everlaſting Puniſhment</hi> or <hi>Torment,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; for here it is neceſſarily imply'd, that the wicked ſhall certainly <hi>be</hi> to Eternity, that they may be <hi>Puniſhed and Tormented</hi> to Eternity; and they ſhall be ſenſible (elſe it would not be Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) of the Puniſhment they undergo. By eternal Deſtruction, you are not to underſtand eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Annihilation,</hi> or being turned for ever into <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> for if a wicked Man ſhould altogether <hi>ceaſe to be,</hi> he muſt needs alſo <hi>ceaſe to be puniſhed.</hi> For 'tis no more a Puniſhment to be <hi>nothing to Eternity,</hi> than it can be called a Puniſhment to have been nothing from Eternity. Wicked men muſt <hi>be for ever,</hi> and alas they muſt <hi>bear for ever</hi> the Lord's Vengeance and Indignation. I ſpeak thus terribly, not without bowels of Compaſſion towards you. I would fain <hi>fright you</hi> by <hi>telling</hi> you of <hi>Wrath,</hi> and the <hi>Vengeance of eternal Fire,</hi> that you may <hi>never, never feel it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Fourth place, I am to demonſtrate <hi>the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this Judgment.</hi> If Faith concerning it were but more ſtrong; what an Influence would it have upon the Hearts and Lives of them that do believe it! The Arguments to prove a future Judgment are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are there not <hi>fears of this Judgment impreſs't even upon natural Conſcience?</hi> What's the reaſon, that when Men commit the moſt ſecret wickedneſs, that is very unlikely to be known; there is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66016:13"/> a <hi>dread</hi> upon their Spirits? The true reaſon is, Conſcience tells them there is a God, that ſees what Man does not ſee, and that he will judge and puniſh the wickedneſs of which Man takes no notice. This Doctrine of a Judgment to come, of future Rewards and puniſhments, is written in the heart of Man by Nature, and he is fain to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer great violence to his own Soul, before he can wear off what is written there; and tho a Sinner become ordinarily very Stupid and Atheiſtical; yet the thoughts and fears of Judgment, will ſometimes, in ſpight of him return upon him. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Conſcience bearing witneſs, and Thoughts accuſing and excuſing;</hi> and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>ſpeaks of the Day when God ſhall judge the Secrets of Men by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 2. 15, 16. Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence judges at preſent, and hints a future judgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is not <hi>ſuch a Diſcrimination made in this World, between the Righteous and the Wicked,</hi> as is ſuitable to the difference that Grace has made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them: Therefore there is a Day coming, when there will be ſuch a Diſcrimination. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that in the courſe of Divine Providence at preſent, <hi>no Man can know either Love or Hatred by all that is before him. All things fall alike to all; there is one Event to the Righteous and to the Wicked, to the good, to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth, and him that Sacrificeth not; as is the good, ſo is the ſinner; and he that Sweareth, as he that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an Oath,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 1, 2. Nay, often times the worſt of men have in this preſent Life the beſt on't. We read, <hi>Luke 16.</hi> of a wicked Rich Man <hi>receiving his good things,</hi> cloathed in <hi>Purple and fine Linnen,</hi> and faring <hi>Sumptuouſly every day.</hi> A poor Man ready
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66016:13"/> to ſtarve for Hunger, was laid at this Rich Man's Gate, his <hi>Body was full of ſores,</hi> and yet this Mans <hi>Soul was ſanctified</hi> with Grace; a <hi>good Man</hi> he was, though <hi>here</hi> he <hi>received evil things;</hi> ſince <hi>thus</hi> it is now, there is a day coming when 'twill be <hi>otherwiſe. Job</hi> having ſpoken of the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Wicked in this World, ſtrongly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that in the next World there will be a <hi>dreadful after-reckoning,</hi> Job. 21. 30. <hi>The Wicked is reſerved to the day of deſtruction, they ſhall be brought forth to the day of Wrath:</hi> This is the day I am ſpeaking of, a day of the <hi>revelation of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2. 5. <hi>Who then will render to every man according to his works to them that by patient continuance in well doing ſeek for glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and honour, and immortality, eternal life; but to them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, indignation and wrath, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil, of the Jew firſt, and alſo of the Gentile,</hi> v. 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt hath <hi>Promiſed his Church that he will come again to Judgment,</hi> and hath raiſed her hopes and expectations of his coming, <hi>Rev. 3. 11. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I come quickly, hold that faſt which thou haſt, that no man take thy Crown:</hi> Heb. 10. 36. <hi>For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> He thus ſpeaks to his Diſciples, <hi>Let not your hearts be troubled, ye believe in God, believe alſo in me;</hi> I am indeed about to leave you, but <hi>I go to prepare a place for you;</hi> and aſſure your ſelves, <hi>I will come again, and receive you to my ſelf, that where I am, there may be alſo,</hi> Joh. 14. 1,—5. Chriſt is the <hi>Amen, the true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſs,</hi> he will certainly be the Judge. The
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66016:14"/> Church will aſſuredly ſee him at laſt upon the <hi>great White Throne;</hi> and her ſelf ſafe and triumphant at his right hand. When he comes, how will he be <hi>glorified in his Saints,</hi> and how will he be <hi>admired by all Believers in that Day!</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There are <hi>ſeveral things that are haſtening Chriſts coming to Judgment:</hi> The World grows old in Wickedneſs, and all the Sins of the World have <hi>tongues</hi> to cry for the appearing of a <hi>Judge,</hi> to <hi>pay</hi> their <hi>deſerved Wages;</hi> the World grows riper and riper for Vengeance, dryer and dryer for that <hi>Fire</hi> that is to <hi>burn it.</hi> The Church of Chriſt is alſo <hi>haſtning Chriſts Appearing,</hi> with their inceſſant Cryes, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, Come quickly, Rev. 22. 20. The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come;</hi> not only unto <hi>Sinners</hi> to come to Chriſt, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> to appear, that he may put an end both to Sin and Suffering: That's the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and language of the Spouſe, <hi>Cant. 8. 14. Make haſte, my Beloved, and be like a Roe, or a young Hart upon the mountains of ſpices:</hi> And this is not the Voice only of the <hi>Church on Earth,</hi> but <hi>they in Heaven</hi> wiſh for, and intreat the ſame thing; <hi>How long, Lord, holy and true!</hi> is heard from the <hi>Souls under the Altar,</hi> Rev. 6. 10.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Place I come to the <hi>Application:</hi> I begin with <hi>Inferences</hi> from the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If there will be a Day of Judgment, hence I inferr, that <hi>there is a preſent Providence:</hi> Will the Lord judge all at laſt? ſurely he <hi>obſerves</hi> all now. The Lord Jeſus would have all the Churches, to know as well, that he <hi>ſearches the Reins and Heart,</hi> as that he will <hi>render to every
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66016:14"/> man according to his Works,</hi> Rev. 2. 23. Whether thy Eye be upon God or no, his Eye is never off from thee; 'tis indeed in <hi>every place, beholding the evil and the good:</hi> What a fooliſh Creature haſt thou reaſon to call thy ſelf? who <hi>conſidereſt not in thy heart that God remembers all thy Wickedneſs, Hoſ. 7. 2.</hi> and Gods remembrance at laſt will <hi>rub up thine;</hi> and what thou now forgetteſt, will ſadly be recalled to thy Mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shall all be Judged? hence I inferr <hi>the Love of God to the Righteous, and his hatred of Iniquity:</hi> Not one righteous Man, but ſhall be acquitted and received by the Judge; not a righteous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſincere intention, but ſhall be rewarded: It will be found at the laſt day, that a <hi>Widdows Mite</hi> given with a Charitable ſpirit, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ability, was a great deal in <hi>Gods Treaſury;</hi> and that a <hi>Cup of cold Water given to a Diſciple, in the Name of a Diſciple,</hi> was well taken, and ſhall not <hi>go unrewarded,</hi> Mat. 10. 42. And there has not been, there is not a Wicked Man on Earth, but his Sin that has been hunting and purſuing to overthrow him, will <hi>then</hi> find him out, <hi>Pſal. 11. 5, 6.</hi> becauſe the Lords <hi>Soul hates</hi> the workers of Iniquity; therefore upon <hi>the wicked he will rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tempeſt, this ſhall be the portion of their Cup:</hi> By <hi>fire, and brimſtone, and tempeſt,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand a ſuddain, grievous, ſurprizing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Puniſhment; and by <hi>ſnares</hi> underſtand, that they in Hell ſhall never be able to extri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate themſelves out of that Miſery into which their Wickedneſs has brought them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If all ſhall be Judged, hence I inferr <hi>the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66016:15"/> truth of the Doctrine of the Reſurrection:</hi> The <hi>whole Man has ſum'd, the <hi>whole Man ſhall be judg'd</hi> and puniſhed for ſin: Believers are <hi>ſanctified</hi> both in Soul and Body,</hi> therefore in Body and Soul they ſhall be gloryfied. The dead ſhall riſe again, all that are <hi>in the Graves ſhall hear the Voice of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and ſhall come forth; they that have done good to the reſurrection of Life, they that have done evil to the reſurrection of Damnation,</hi> Joh. 5. 28, 29. The Grave is only a priſon for a time, not a Body that is there that ſhall lye there always; the ſame Body that was employed in the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful works of darkneſs, ſhall be raiſed by the Power of the righteous Judge, to ſhare in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merited Puniſhment: And the ſame Body of the Saints, the Members of which were uſed as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Righteouſneſs unto Holineſs, by Vertue of its Union with Chriſt, ſhall riſe again, and be <hi>made like unto Chriſts glorious body, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf,</hi> Phil. 3. 21. It is not <hi>another Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> I grant that qualities are alter'd, but the ſubſtance is the ſame, therefore the Apoſtle does not ſtick to ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>This cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi> ſhall put on <hi>incorruption,</hi> this <hi>mortal</hi> ſhall put on <hi>immortality;</hi> ſo <hi>when this corruptible ſhall have put on incorruption, and this mortal ſhall have put on immortality, then ſhall be brought to paſs the ſaying that is written, Death is ſwallowed up in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 53, 54.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Will there be a Judgment, 'tis <hi>wonderful there ſhould be ſo much ſecurity in them that hear of it:</hi> Really the very mentioning of Chriſts Tribunal, before which all muſt ſtand, ſhould make all Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66016:15"/> to tremble. If a Man were ſeized for a Crime that's capital, deſerving Death by the Law of God and Man, and being in Bolts and Fetters in <hi>Newgate,</hi> he ſhould be ſecure and unconcerned, though the Seſſious were at hand, you would conclude him to be very ſtupid and inconſiderate. What, Sinner, ſecure! and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be Judged! O Drunkard! Whoremonger! Swearer! Sabbath-breaker! Covetous World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling! what, ſecure! and ſpeedily to appear at the Judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, who has ſaid, <hi>That they that do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God! Sin is folly, ſecurity</hi> in Sin is the <hi>folly of that folly:</hi> Take heed of Security, 'tis not I only, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf alſo that gives you this neceſſary caution, <hi>Luk; 21. 34, 35, 36. And take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeiting and drunkeneſs, and the cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares; for as a ſhare ſhall it come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth: Watch ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and Pray always, that ye may be accounted worthy to eſcape all thoſe things that ſhall come to paſs, and to ſtand before the Son of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> II. By way of Counſel. Two words of Counſel I would give this Congregation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>one</hi> is, more <hi>firmly to believe a Judgment,</hi> and more <hi>frequently to think of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is, <hi>Be ſure in time to prepare for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. More <hi>firmly believe, more frequently think of Judgment:</hi> You have reaſon to believe it, for the <hi>Judge is ordained,</hi> and though neither Men
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66016:16"/> nor Angels know the day, yet the <hi>day is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Act. 17. 30, 31. <hi>The time of this ignorance God winked at, but now commands all men every where to repent, becauſe he hath appointed a day in which he will judge the World in righteouſneſs, by that Man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance unto all, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi> The ſtronger your aſſent is unto this, the more ſerious and often will be your Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
            <p>To think of Judgment is proper for a <hi>Saint,</hi> that he may be encouraged to fight the good fight of Faith, and perſevere in well doing to the end.</p>
            <p>To think of Judgment is proper for a <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Man,</hi> to awaken him, and to make him <hi>with fear and trembling to work out his Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's proper for an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> to think of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe then all Masks and Vizours will be pull'd off, all ſhews will be at an end, and <hi>naked Truth</hi> will appear at that day: The Graves will be open'd, and do ye think the <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted painted Sepulchers</hi> will remain ſhut? Oh! then all the concealed Pride, and Filthineſs, and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhneſs, and Senſuality, and Injuſtice, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Profeſſors, will with all their aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be brought to light before Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: Oh, how many <hi>demure and ſerious Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> that have been a <hi>covering</hi> to <hi>naughty Hearts,</hi> will then be filled with <hi>Confuſion!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis proper for the <hi>Old</hi> to think of Judgment; they have <hi>one foot</hi> in the Grave already, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>whole body</hi> muſt drop into it, and the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit muſt return to God who gave it.</hi> You alſo that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66016:16"/> are <hi>Young</hi> ſhould think of Judgment; have the youngeſt of yoa any aſſurance of your Lives? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, Children, Youths, do not many of them dye and ſtep into Eternity? and as you ſee them leave the World, ſo certainly they appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and one way or other have their Doom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> tells you, that Childhood and Youth are Vanity: Would you that are Young be ſerious? the Meditation of Judgment would conduce much to it, <hi>Eccleſ. 11. 9. Rejoyce, O young Man, in thy Youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy Youth, and walk in the wayes of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes:</hi> He ſays, Rejoyce, but ſpeaks <hi>Ironically,</hi> and means the <hi>quite contrary;</hi> thoa haſt no reaſon at all to rejoyce, whilſt thou walkeſt that are ſeen, and whilſt thou walkeſt in thoſe evil ways which thy Heart naturally does like: Then the Wiſe man ſpeaks ſeriouſly, <hi>But know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask me, What are the Benefits that will accrue by a firm Belief, and frequent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Judgment? I thus Anſwer to this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This will be a <hi>great Preſervative againſt Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> Look beyond the preſent advantage and delight that Sin boaſts of, and ſee as far as the Judgment-ſeat, this is the way to ſilence the Tempter, and to avoid his ſhare: Would the Lyar dare to ſpeak falily, if he conſidered, that <hi>all Lyars</hi> ſhall be adjudged to <hi>the lake that burns with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death?</hi> Rev. 21. 8. Would the Unclean Perſon dare to deſile himſelf, and run to the Harlots houſe, if he did but believe and conſider that it <hi>boremangers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66016:17"/> and Adulterers God will judge?</hi> Improve Chriſts Croſs, and think of Chriſts Tribunal, and this will cool and kill Corruptions, and take away the force of your Temptations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Belief and Meditation of Judgment will cauſe you <hi>to uſe this World as not abuſing it,</hi> to make a good improvement of it. You that have this World in great abundance, and have the <hi>cleareſt and largeſt Eſtates;</hi> do you think you are <hi>Proprietors</hi> of what you have? Do you think 'tis <hi>given</hi> or only <hi>lent</hi> you for a time? You are only Stewards intruſted with that which is Gods and not yours, and are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table at the laſt day for all you have received. What <hi>ſad accounts</hi> will moſt give up of <hi>their Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip;</hi> when they muſt be <hi>no longer Stewards! Imprimis,</hi> So much daily for Eating and Drinking to Self, and not to the Glory of God. <hi>Item,</hi> So much for brave Apparel, that Pride might be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and gratified. <hi>Item,</hi> So much for making proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſts thereof. <hi>Item,</hi> So much for coſtly and vaſt Paſt-times; a great deal of Wealth, and much more precious Time being waſted together. But unto <hi>good uſes,</hi> to <hi>maintain a Godly and laborious Miniſtry</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, to the <hi>poor and needy,</hi> given <hi>very little or nothing.</hi> With <hi>what an Eye</hi> do you think that the <hi>Judge</hi> will look upon <hi>ſuch accounts</hi> as theſe? Think of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that you may holily improve the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mammon, and Chriſt may ſay you have been <hi>Faithful Stewards,</hi> even of <hi>worldly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Belief and Meditation of Judgment, will make you <hi>exceeding diligent, that you may be found of your Judge in peace, without ſpot and blameleſs.</hi> With what Seriouſneſs and Fervency will he come to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66016:17"/> Throne of Grace, that has the Judgment-ſeat alſo in his Eye? How will he hear and practiſe, that remembers he muſt be called to an account, how he has done both? He will take care to be ready whenſoever his Lord calls, and that whenſoever his Lord comes. he may find him doing the Work he ſet him about, and <hi>ſo doing it</hi> as He commands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other word of Counſel is this, <hi>Be ſure in time to prepare for Eternal Judgment:</hi> Do this ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, do it preſently, and as your main buſineſs. That you may prepare indeed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be <hi>Accuſers and Judges of your ſelves;</hi> take notice of your Sins, with Grief, with Hatred, and holy Indignation! accuſe your ſelves of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, with ſelf-loathing and ſelf-abhorrency. Look down by Faith into the loweſt hell, and ſee the terrible but righteous Severity, that is ſhewn there againſt obſtinate workers of Iniquity; then look up to God, and judge your ſelves in his ſight, acknowledging that you have deſerved one of the hotteſt places in that Lake of Fire. Acknowledge he would be <hi>clear in the</hi> ſoreſt <hi>judgment</hi> he ſhould pronounce upon you, and that He would be <hi>juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> tho you ſhould be <hi>damn'd eternally,</hi> Pſal. 51. 4. This <hi>judging of your ſelves,</hi> is the way to prevent <hi>Condemnation with the World,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 31, 32.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you would be prepared for Judgment, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Jeſus, that you may the juſtified before God at preſent.</hi> Receive Chriſt, who is offer'd in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; rely upon his <hi>Obedience and Sufferings for juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life.</hi> And being <hi>juſtified by Faith, you ſhall have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. 1. <hi>Being juſtified by his Bloud, you ſhall be Saved from wrath through him,</hi> Rom. 5. 9.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66016:18"/> What does <hi>ponere obicem,</hi> put a <hi>Bar</hi> before Hell Gate, and hinder us from falling into that place of Woe? The <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, that's the Bar; you are to place your Confidence in Chriſt Crucified: If juſtified by him now, he will <hi>ratifie the juſtification</hi> at the laſt day, and you ſhall not be condemned then, <hi>Rom. 8. 33, 34. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that juſtifieth. Who is he that Condemneth? It is Chriſt that dyed, yea, rather that is riſen again; who is at the Right Hand of God, and maketh Interceſſion for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Would you be prepared for Judgment; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be converted;</hi> let your minds be changed, and turn to God with your whole Heart. This is the way indeed to ſtand before him, <hi>Acts 3. 19. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be converted, that your Sins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> The Apoſtle looks as far as the laſt day. <hi>Blotting out of Sins,</hi> is Chriſt's <hi>abſolving and acqutting them</hi> from all Treſpaſſes. The time of refreſhing, is that great day of <hi>compleat and glorious Redemption,</hi> when all that are Chriſts ſhall lift up their Heads with Joy: Repent and be converts in Truth, if you would have that a day of refreſhing, and not of confuſion. Walk after the Fleſh no longer, but after the Spirit; then you need not be afraid of Condemnation, your being guided by his Spirit, will ſhew you are in Chriſt, and ſafe in Him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. There is therefore now no Condemnation to them that are in Christ Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit; to be carnally minded is Death, but to be Spiritually minded, is life and peace.</p>
            <p>USE III. Of <hi>Terrour</hi> to the <hi>ungodly,</hi> the <hi>Hypocrites
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66016:18"/> and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers;</hi> Chriſt will judge them all, and they may tremble to think what kind of judgment they ſhall have: what ſharp and piercing words are thoſe, which declare before-hand what will be their Doom, <hi>Mat. 23. 33. Ye Serpents, ye Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vipers, how can ye eſcape the Damndtion of Hell?</hi> That I may, if it be poſſible, awaken ſuch, I would lay before them theſe terrifying conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When they appear at Chriſt's Bar, <hi>all their ſecret wickedneſs will be made known.</hi> How many will then be found what they were not in the leaſt ſuſpected! Thy ſecret wantonneſs, and Self-pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; thy ſecret injuſtice and deſrauding; thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret abominations, of all kinds, will then be as <hi>viſible to every Eye,</hi> as if written in <hi>Capital Letters</hi> with the <hi>brighteſt Sun-beam.</hi> And what ſname and confuſion will cover the wicked Mans Face! they that are impudent, and cannot bouſh now; how will they be confounded then! The truth is, as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks; <hi>They will riſe to ſhame and everlaſting contempt,</hi> Dan. 12. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At the day of Judgment it will be <hi>too late, and in vain for the wicked to pray and cry for Mercy;</hi> they will find the Lord eternally removed from the Throne of Grace, and to their Terrour behold him on the Judgment Seat. If the Ungodly roar out, then, <hi>Lord pity! Lord pardon!</hi> Lord, <hi>ſend us not away into that flaming Furnace that me ſee before us!</hi> it will be altogether in vain: but 'tis not in vain to cry thus now. <hi>Oh, ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call ye upon him whilſt he he is near,</hi> Iſa. 55. 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will add to the Terrour of the Wicked, <hi>That the Sentence of Condemnation is pronounced by the Only Saviour:</hi> The <hi>merciful and faithful High Prieſt,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66016:19"/> that now is ſo forward to <hi>make Reconciliation for Sin,</hi> that is ſo ready to give <hi>reſt to them that labour and are heavy laden.</hi> The <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt Jeſus will have no pity at all, no compaſſion towards the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate <hi>Children of Men;</hi> but deal with them as with the Apoſtate Angels, <hi>whoſe Nature be never</hi> took upon him. The only Peace-maker will himſelf be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, and full of Wrath, as not to be intreated, not to be appeaſed. The Sentence of Eternal Death, and enduring everlaſting Burnings, will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding; but 'twill <hi>add</hi> to the <hi>Confuſion,</hi> that a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi> does <hi>pronounce</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. After the Judge has paſs'd the Sentence, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will pronounce it over again,</hi> and will be a <hi>Judge</hi> to the Wicked, <hi>always condemning</hi> them. Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will be filled with unſpeakable remorſe; it will continually be upbraiding them with their madneſs and folly in <hi>keeping</hi> their <hi>Sins,</hi> and <hi>loſing</hi> their <hi>Souls;</hi> and will ever be telling them, that <hi>the Lords ways towards them are equal, but their own ways according to which they are Judged, have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal,</hi> and full of Iniquity, <hi>Ezek. 18. 29, 30.</hi> The Conſcience of Sinners will <hi>ſide</hi> with their Judge againſt them. It will tell the moſt wretched among the Damned, that they cannot <hi>complain of God,</hi> or of the <hi>leaſt injury</hi> he has done them; all that they ſuffer, they ſuffer <hi>juſtly;</hi> and what they ſuffer, <hi>they</hi> have brought upon <hi>themſelves.</hi> The horrible and perpetual <hi>remorſe</hi> of Conſcience, will prove that the <hi>Worm never dies,</hi> that does torment them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When Sinners come to be condemn'd at the laſt day, <hi>how many things will riſe up in judgment againſt them?</hi> (pray mind this, and minding trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66016:19"/> and trembling turn to God this very inſtant.) Thouſands of <hi>Mercies</hi> will come, and as it were plead thus: <hi>Lord! we have been all abuſed, we never met with any thing but abuſes, and never could lead theſe men to Repentance!</hi> The Rods of Affliction will have a <hi>Voice</hi> againſt them too. <hi>Lord! we have ſtricken Sinners often, we have made them Bleed and Groan, and ſmart exceedingly for their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities; but could never make them leave off Sinning againſt Thee, and againſt their own Souls!</hi> How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sermons will riſe up in judgment againſt them; becauſe they either <hi>ſlept</hi> them away; or if they were awake, they ſuffer'd them to <hi>ſlip</hi> out of their <hi>Memories,</hi> and never <hi>applyed</hi> them to their <hi>Hearts!</hi> And as for us, the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Goſpel, our <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt them will be <hi>true</hi> and <hi>terrible Lord! we lifted up our Voices like Trumpets; we gave them the Watchmans Warning, we told them of the Sword that was coming, and that if they turned not from Sin, it would ſurely ſlay them: we wooed them to come to Jeſus, that under his Wing they might be ſecure; but nothing would prevail; their Ears were deaf, their Hearts they hardened, they would not be converted and made clean, they would ruſh on in Sin ſtill, they would needs Dye, and there was no helping it!</hi> The Condemnation muſt needs be dreadful, when ſo many things riſe up againſt them that are condemned!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> IV. Of <hi>Conſolation</hi> to the <hi>Saints.</hi> I muſt ſpeak to them in another ſtrain. Lift up your Heads, and let your Hearts be filled with Joy; all ye believing, repenting, humble, holy, heavenly-minded Ones! for the Day of your Redemption draws nigh,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66016:20"/> with an earneſt expectation wait for it, and Triumph at the Thoughts of your great and everlaſting <hi>Jubilee.</hi> You will indeed behold the greateſt part of mankind turned into Hell; but what Joy will it be to find your ſelves for ever ſafe and fully bleſſed! A dark Shadow ſets off a beautiful Picture. The ſight of the Rich man in Hell Flames, muſt needs make <hi>Lazarus</hi> to find a greater ſweetneſs in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſome!</p>
            <p>Two Grounds of Conſolation I ſhall propound to you, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is to be <hi>your Judge,</hi> that is <hi>your Husband</hi> and <hi>your Head.</hi> The very ſame whom you now find interceding for you in Prayer; whom you ſee walking in the midſt of the Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and bleſſing his Ordinances to you. The very ſame whom you have found pitying, and healing your Wounds with his own Blood; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring you in your Temptations, and telling you that you are the Beloved of his Soul! And ſince <hi>he</hi> is to Judge you, be comforted. He will behold you with an aſpect, that is highly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable! His <hi>own Spouſe,</hi> whom he has ranſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his <hi>own Life,</hi> Chriſt will not turn into devouring Fire! He will not take the Members of his own Body, and throw them into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Burnings! Having <hi>Redeemed</hi> them by his <hi>Blood,</hi> having <hi>renewed and Sanctified</hi> them by his <hi>Spirit;</hi> having <hi>raiſed</hi> them up at the great day; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he will receive them to himſelf, and they ſhall be <hi>ever with the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 17, 18. <hi>wherefore be comforted with theſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You that are true Believers, whoſe Faith purifies your Hearts and works by Love; know
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66016:20"/> 
               <hi>that there is a Crown deſigned for you.</hi> The <hi>Diadems</hi> that Monarchs have upon their Heads; the <hi>Triple Crown</hi> of Him at <hi>Rome,</hi> is but a <hi>Trifle</hi> to the <hi>Crown of life.</hi> This Crown is purchaſed, 'tis promiſed, 'tis prepared; and ſhortly you ſhall put it on, and never put it off more. How Splendid, how Bright, how Sparkling, will that Crown be! 'Tis called a Crown of Life, for Death ſhall be no more. A Crown of Glory, for the Saints ſhall be more than Conquerours, and Triumphant over all Enemies, and be advanced to the higheſt Honour and State, whereof they are capable. Finally, 'tis called a Crown of <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> 'tis a <hi>Righteous thing with God,</hi> to beſtow it through <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and perfect Righteouſneſs and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will be a great part of the happineſs of Saints in Glory. This Crown the Apoſtle ſaw to his great encouragement, and he would have all other Believers comforted with the ſame ſight, <hi>2 Tim. 4. 7, 8. I have fought a good Fight, I have finiſhed my Courſe, I have kept the Faith; henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that Day, and not to me only, but unto all them alſo that love his appearing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66016:21"/>MAT. 11. 23. Form. Part.</bibl>
               <q>And thou Capernaum, which art exalted unto Heaven, ſhalt be brought down to Hell!</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Our Lord Jeſus is called the <hi>Lamb of God who takes away the Sins of the World:</hi> But in this Lamb there is <hi>Wrath,</hi> and that Wrath is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry terrible. Oh the weight of the Mediatours Vengeance! This Wrath is threatned againſt the impenitent and unbelievers, who refuſe to be <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from their Sins, reſolving to live,</hi> tho they <hi>Dye</hi> in them. The <hi>Light</hi> of the Goſpel being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, highly aggravates the <hi>Works of Darkneſs;</hi> makes them more inexcuſable, and a greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation. None ſhall fare <hi>worſe</hi> at the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> than thoſe that have had the longeſt and the cleareſt <hi>day of Grace;</hi> but <hi>would not know in that their day,</hi> the things which <hi>belonged to their Peace.</hi> Thou <hi>Capernaum which are exalted unto Heaven, ſhalt be brought down to Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words which I have read, do ſpeak Chriſt's ſorrow and his diſpleaſure, wherein you may take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the <hi>Perſons</hi> with whom he is diſpleaſed, <hi>Thou Capernaum;</hi> the City is put for the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Chriſts diſpleaſure; they did not underſtand the great priviledge of <hi>being Exalted unto Heaven;</hi> they did not improve the advantage they had of getting thither.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66016:21"/>3. Here is a <hi>Puniſhment</hi> threatned, a ſore evil; and that is no leſs than Hell it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here is the <hi>manner</hi> ſpecified of their <hi>going to Hell;</hi> thou ſhalt be <hi>brought down to Hell,</hi> with a ſtrong Hand, with great Wrath, and in one of the hotteſt and loweſt Places there thou ſhalt lye for ever.</p>
            <p>There are two Doctrines which I raiſe from the Words.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Thoſe that hear the Goſpel, are exalted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven:</hi> Happy you, if you underſtand your Priviledge which at this day you enjoy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>They who will not turn to God at the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-call, ſhall certainly be turned into Hell: Thou Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum, who art exalted unto Heaven, ſhalt be brought down to Hell;</hi> and if Chriſt ſays it <hi>ſhall be ſo,</hi> moſt certainly it <hi>will be ſo.</hi> The firſt of theſe I ſhall but juſt touch upon, for it is the ſecond that I principally purpoſe to Proſecute.</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. The firſt Doctrine is this; <hi>They that hear the Goſpel, are exalted unto Heaven.</hi> The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is an heavenly Calling, <hi>Heb. 3. 1.</hi> it comes from Heaven, and ſays to thoſe that hear it, <hi>Come up hither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Life and Immortality is <hi>brought to light by the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 10. Here you have a Map of thoſe happy Regions of Light, and Love, and Joy; where there is nothing preſent that is bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome, where there is nothing wanting that <hi>is</hi> deſirable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Goſpel plainly <hi>chalks out the way that leads to Life:</hi> Chriſt is <hi>the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> Joh. 14. 6. the true way to life indeed: We
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66016:22"/> have liberty to <hi>enter into the holieſt of all, by the blood of Jeſus:</hi> had it not been for his undertaking, and performance of what he undertook, there had been a <hi>flaming Sword at Heavens gate,</hi> and no fallen Man could ever have entred there. And as Chriſt, in whom we are to believe, is the way, ſo is alſo <hi>Holineſs:</hi> Chriſt by his Blood has purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the heavenly Inheritance, and has bought the Saints themſelves that are to be the Inheritors; and 'tis by his ſanctifying Spirit, by true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they are made <hi>meet for that Inheritance.</hi> The <hi>pure in Heart,</hi> and ſuch will be likewiſe pure in <hi>Life,</hi> are the <hi>bleſſed Ones</hi> that <hi>ſhall ſee God,</hi> Mat. 5. 8. and who beſides are deſirous or fit to ſee the Lord?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heaven in the Goſpel is <hi>offer'd;</hi> 'tis <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, freely</hi> offer'd unto <hi>All;</hi> 'tis offer'd to the <hi>meaneſt Perſons,</hi> 'tis offer'd to the <hi>greateſt Sinners,</hi> and that without Money, without Price: 'Tis indeed too good, too great a thing for Man to purchaſe by any thing that he can give or do. Thoſe have very low thoughts of Heaven, and very high thoughts of their own Works, that think they can do enough to merit Heaven. Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life is the <hi>free Gift of God,</hi> not deſerved by Man; and 'tis given <hi>through Christ,</hi> Rom. 6. 23. Had not Chriſt procured it, fallen Men would all have been as certainly excluded as the fallen Angels.</p>
            <p>Briefly to Apply this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be <hi>thankful for the Goſpel,</hi> which makes the <hi>richeſt diſcovery</hi> that ever was made in this World; the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> cannot ſhew any thing comparable to a bleſſed Immortality; the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66016:22"/> from the one, the Gold from the other, are contemptible, when Heaven is named. The Goſpel tells you where is the true, the <hi>tried Gold,</hi> and of the <hi>Pearl which is of greateſt price;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a <hi>Treaſure in Heaven, which neither moth nor ruſt doth corrupt,</hi> nor can <hi>thieves break through and ſteal,</hi> Mat. 6. 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the Kingdom of Heaven <hi>ſuffer Violence,</hi> and do you uſe an holy <hi>force to take it;</hi> here you will meet with great oppoſition; Heaven is that which occaſions the envy of Hell, becauſe of its real and eternal Excellency, and does very well deſerve your labour. Let the <hi>Treaſure</hi> in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven cauſe your <hi>Hearts</hi> to be <hi>there,</hi> ſtrive to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the ſtrait gate, hate every falſe way, becauſe it leads from Heaven, and towards De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; let the Hopes of a Crown of glory make you willing to bear the Croſs; look upon Sloth as moſt abſurd, when no leſs than Heaven will be given to them who ſhew their <hi>diligence in full aſſurance of hope unto the end:</hi> Preſs ſtill <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards the mark;</hi> you cannot run too faſt for ſuch a Prize.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſtay on this no longer: 'Tis the ſecond Doctrine that more largely I ſhall inſiſt on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct. 2.</hi> And that's this, <hi>Thoſe that will not turn to God at the Call of the Goſpel, ſhall certainly be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Hell;</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 8, 9. <hi>They that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Doctrine, I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:66016:23"/>1. Diſcourſe concerning Hell, what it is, that you may the <hi>better underſtand it;</hi> and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be afraid of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall <hi>prove the Certainty</hi> of the Doctrine, that Sinners who will not turn to God, ſhall moſt ſurely be turned into Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall Vindicate the Righteouſneſs of God, in thus dealing with, and eternally Puniſhing them that will not turn to him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall conclude with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes and Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Place I am to Diſcourſe concerning Hell, and to ſhew you <hi>what it is.</hi> In Hell</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Deprivation of good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an <hi>Infliction of evil, pain and torment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an <hi>Eternity</hi> of both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Hell there is a <hi>Deprivation of good:</hi> All the temporal loſſes that have been ſuſtained by all the Children of Men in this World, are not comparable to the <hi>Poena Damni,</hi> Puniſhment of <hi>loſs,</hi> which one Sinner in Hell ſhall undergoe: Several things thoſe in Hell are deprived of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are deprived of <hi>all that Love, and Grace, and Mercy that is in God:</hi> The Pſalmiſt that knew by experience the excellency of God's Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, affirms 'tis <hi>better than Life,</hi> Pſal. 63. 3. His Mercys are <hi>tender,</hi> and a <hi>multitude,</hi> and <hi>ſure</hi> to the Veſſels of Mercy. How were thoſe fill'd with admiration, and with a ſenſe of their obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, <hi>Who in times paſt were not a People,</hi> but were made <hi>the People of God; who had not obtained Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> but after <hi>did obtain Mercy,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 10. But alas, thô God be <hi>Love</hi> it ſelf, 1 <hi>Joh. 4. 8.</hi> he hath no Love for them that are in Hell, they lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66016:23"/> his Wrath and Hatred, and both are unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terably ſixt upon them: Though the Lord does delight in ſhewing Mercy, yet his Bowels do not at all ſtir or move towards the Damned; though they lye in extreameſt Woe, and are continually <hi>weeping and wailing,</hi> yet their Tears <hi>draw not</hi> forth his <hi>Compaſſions:</hi> He has <hi>caſt them off for ever,</hi> and will be <hi>favourable no more;</hi> he has <hi>forgotten to be gracious,</hi> and in implacable, but righteous Anger, has <hi>ſhut up his tender Mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They that are in Hell, are deprived <hi>of the beatifical Viſion of God:</hi> The door of Heaven they found ſhut againſt them, when they ſaid, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us!</hi> and 'twill never be opened: They ſhall never be ſuffered to <hi>ſee him face to face,</hi> but be always excluded from his Preſence. What Happineſs is there in <hi>ſeeing God!</hi> how tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and ſatisfying is this ſight! <hi>Pſal. 17.</hi> ult. <hi>As for me, I ſhall behold thy face in righteouſneſs, I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs:</hi> But the Damned are not, never ſhall be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſuch a View; they are baniſhed that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Preſence, where there is fulneſs of joy, and where there are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> God has <hi>fixt a great gulph</hi> between himſelf and them, and through that 'tis impoſſible for them <hi>to paſs,</hi> Luk. 16. 26.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They in Hell are deprived of <hi>all hopes by a Mediator:</hi> Our Lord tells us, That he <hi>came not into the World to condemn the World, but that the World through him might be ſaved;</hi> and has given a large Commiſſion <hi>to Preach the Goſpel,</hi> to offer that Grace and Salvation whereof he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>to every Creature,</hi> Mark 16. 15. The Lord Jeſus now encourages all to come to him, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66016:24"/> they may have reſt to their Souls, and life through his Name; and <hi>them that come to him, he will in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> Joh. 6. 37. and when they refuſe to come, he expreſſes great ſorrow; he <hi>wept over Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe ſhe <hi>knew not the time of her</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Viſitation.</hi> But when Sinners have finn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the day of Grace, and ended all their days on Earth, and by their final Impenitency brought themſelves to Hell; then the ſame Chains are clapt on them, in which the Reprobate Angels ly fetter'd, and Chriſt will no more ſave <hi>them</hi> than <hi>theſe.</hi> Oh dreadful! to loſe all hope in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, never to be called to come to him more: Aſtoniſhingly ſcarful! to be in a place where the glad tidings of the Goſpel are never heard, where the Spirit never ſtrives, and where the Redeemer never ſtretches forth an hand to ſave!</p>
            <p n="4">4. They in Hell are deprived <hi>of the glory of the new Jeruſalem:</hi> 'Tis a mighty loſs, to loſe ſuch a <hi>weighty thing</hi> as a <hi>far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 17. Suppoſe a Rich Man, worth Millions, ſhould break, and not be worth a Farthing; ſuppoſe all the Kings and Emperors breathing, ſhould loſe their Crowns in one day, this would be but a petty Loſs, compared with the loſs of a Crown of Life: In Heaven there is ſuch a Crown, and the Damned might have had it, if they had but valued it; but alas! that Crown they muſt never wear: In Heaven there is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where they in Hell muſt never reign: When they ſee what they have loſt, and how fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wilfully, and for the ſake of what poor thing they loſt it, how will they be fill'd with Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tearing vexation, and be quite overwhelmed with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66016:24"/> ſorrow, <hi>Luk. 13. 28. There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth; when ye ſhall ſee Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, and all the Prophets, in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, and you your ſelves thruſt out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As in Hell there is a Deprivation of good, ſo there is an <hi>Infliction of evil, pain and torment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is in Hell <hi>great torment in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> A wounded Conſcience in <hi>this World</hi> has been found intolerable. <hi>Spira,</hi> he ſignifies that Racks, Gibbets, Flames of Martyrdom, were nothing to what he felt, and in a Pang of Deſpair attempts Self-murthering; but being hindred, he breaks out into Blaſphemy, <hi>I wiſh I were above God, for I know he will not have Mercy on me:</hi> here was Hells lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in his Mouth, and much of Hell-torment in his Heart. <hi>Judas</hi> his Conſcience was wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could he bear it? No, he becomes his own Executioner, with his own hand ends his Life, and ſends his Soul to <hi>his appointed place:</hi> And yet the torment of Conſcience in this World, is but the <hi>Preoeludium,</hi> the beginning of ſorrows. Every Conſcience in Hell will be <hi>thoroughly awake,</hi> and keep it ſelf <hi>for ever waking;</hi> it will be <hi>exactly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible;</hi> not a Sin that has been Committed all the life-time, but will have made a Wound in the Conſcience; and not Wound but will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerably ſmarting, without hope of any eaſe. Conſcience will be in a perpetual Agony, in this Agony 'twill rage, and raging it will reproach the Damned: It will tell them of their preſumptuous ſinning, of their rejecting Chriſt, their neglecting great Salvation, and how all <hi>its checking</hi> of them was <hi>in vain:</hi> And now 'tis incurably wounded, it can never be quiet, but they ſhall always find it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66016:25"/> a tormented, a tormenting Fury within them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is in Hell, not only torment in the Conſcience, but alſo torment in <hi>the Mind and Heart:</hi> What <hi>rueful</hi> thoughts will poſſes their Minds! whatever they think of will be torturing; a pleaſing, a delightful thought can never enter into them more: If they <hi>think of Sin,</hi> it will be bitter to conſider how they have been deceived and ruin'd by it: If they think of their <hi>preſent Miſery,</hi> and the remedlineſs of it, and that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had the greateſt hand in bringing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into it, theſe thoughts like <hi>daggers,</hi> muſt needs pierce their Souls: If they <hi>think of God,</hi> Oh how will they be troubled! how will his <hi>Juſtice, Jealouſie, Fury, Holineſs, Truth, irreſiſtible Power, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangablen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs terrifie them!</hi> Thoughts on Earth were their <hi>Sins,</hi> and Thoughts in Hell will be their <hi>Racks</hi> and <hi>Sorrows;</hi> their Hearts will always be <hi>brim full</hi> of <hi>Grief. Shame</hi> and <hi>Confuſicn of face</hi> will add to their Miſery, when all their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs ſhall be known to all, which will make the juſtneſs of their Puniſhment. evident. And how will they be tormented with <hi>Anger at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart,</hi> and <hi>Indignation againſt themſelves!</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though the <hi>Devil</hi> was their great Enemy yet they themſelves were <hi>far greater Enemies to themſelves</hi> than <hi>he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There will in Hell be torment in <hi>Sinners M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mories:</hi> I wiſh that none of you that hear me thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day, may in that place of Woe, remember th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Warning now given you,</hi> to your <hi>Confuſion,</hi> becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you <hi>would not take it;</hi> heark what was ſaid, <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 16. 25. Son, remember thou in thy life-time received thy good things, and Lazarus evil things; but now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66016:25"/> is comforted, and thou art tormented:</hi> Really the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of what he <hi>had,</hi> what he <hi>was,</hi> and what he <hi>did</hi> on Earth, was in Holl very tormenting to this wretched Rich Man. The Damned <hi>there,</hi> will remember their delicious Fare, and how ſenſual and bruitiſh they were in pleaſing of their Appetites; they will remember the time they ſpent in Adorning of themſelves, taking much Pains to dreſs and trick the Carkaſs, but no Pains at all to purge the Heart; they will remember their Feaſts, their Mirth, their carnal Jollity, which quite ſtupified their Hearts, and baniſhed all thoughts and care about another World and Eternity; they will remember all the <hi>Mercies</hi> they enjoyed, which they did nothing but abuſe to their <hi>own harm,</hi> as well as to the <hi>diſhonour of that God</hi> who gave them.</p>
            <p>Above all, they will remember <hi>what Pains were taken to have prevented their Deſtruction:</hi> The Lord was <hi>unwilling they ſhould Periſh,</hi> but <hi>Death</hi> was that which <hi>themſelves</hi> preferr'd before <hi>Life.</hi> Oh how long did Chriſt come, Sabbath after Sabbath, and <hi>knock at the door,</hi> but they would not open! How often did the Spirit ſtrive with them, to ſtop them in Hells road, and to turn them into the way of Peace, but they were <hi>ſtiff-necked,</hi> and <hi>always reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> They will remember their <hi>Preachers</hi> Pains and Prayers, and labour and travel of Soul; how they lifted up their Voices, to awaken them out of their Sin and Security; how they intreated them to be reconciled to God, and to turn into the fate and bleſſed Paths of Righteouſneſs; but they were Deaf and obſtinate, nothing would prevail with them, and the remembrance of all this will be <hi>bitter, bitter, bitter</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In Hell there will be torment in <hi>the Body and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66016:26"/> the Members of it,</hi> and ſuch as no body ever felt, or was capable of bearing here on Earth: The Stone, the Cholick and the Strangury, the greateſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ever the hand of Man inflicted, are no more comparable to the Pains of Hell, than the ſmalleſt Prick of a Pin is to a Dagger that ſtrikes quite through, and gives the Heart a deadly Wound. The Senſes of the Damned ſhall have that which will be exceedingly afflicting: What woful Spectacles will their <hi>Eyes</hi> behold! What diſmal Noyſes will fill their <hi>Ears!</hi> how fierce and unquenchable are the Flames that they ſhall <hi>feel! all their parts</hi> ſhall be in pain, not ſo much as <hi>one</hi> free: The whole Body was defiled, and at Sins ſervice, all the Members were yielded as <hi>inſtruments of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi> 'tis but righteous that all ſhould be Puniſhed. Why are the <hi>Bodies</hi> of the Wicked <hi>raiſed</hi> at the laſt day? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they may bear their part in the Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the whole Man by Sin has deſerved. This Reſurrection is certain, but 'tis a dreadful Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which is a <hi>Reſurrection to Damnation,</hi> Joh. 5. 29.</p>
            <p>In theſe Torments you may well ſuppoſe that <hi>Death</hi> will be wiſht for, and that the Damned would <hi>rejoyce if they could find a Grave;</hi> but alas, after the Reſurrection, the <hi>firſt Death</hi> is no more. The Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a ſad ſenſe do put on Incorruption and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, they can never dye and ceaſe to feel their Pains; they muſt always live a Life ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times worſe than Death, and there is no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. O you Wicked Men! where's your <hi>true Love</hi> to your <hi>Bodies,</hi> that you ſeem to be ſo tender of? I beſeech you mind your <hi>Souls,</hi> and <hi>love your Bodies bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> than by Sin to expoſe them to the Vengeance of eternal Fire. You ſee how in Hell there is a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of good,</hi> an <hi>Inſtiction of evil, pain and torment:</hi> I add,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:66016:26"/>3. In Hell there is <hi>an Eternity of both,</hi> the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation will be without <hi>Hope of Reſtitution;</hi> and the Torment will be without <hi>any end,</hi> without the <hi>leaſt Mitigation.</hi> Eternity is an amazing word; the thing it ſelf much more amazing! Who can ſee to the end of Eternity! who can ſee half way into Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! <hi>Time</hi> is continually <hi>paſſing;</hi> but Eternity never in the leaſt <hi>ſpends:</hi> 'tis not capable of any <hi>diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> after <hi>myriads of Ages,</hi> 'tis ſtill as <hi>bulky</hi> and <hi>whole</hi> as ever. If Hell were Ten thouſand times hotter than it is, yet were it but a <hi>Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and at laſt to end, 'twould be <hi>Nothing</hi> in compariſon. But ſince thoſe that are thrown into it, muſt lye in it for ever, Hells Eternity is the very Hell of Hell. In Eternity, whether of <hi>Joy</hi> or <hi>Woe,</hi> there is <hi>tota ſimul &amp; perfecta poſſeſſio,</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> of it <hi>perfectly</hi> poſſeſs'd at <hi>once.</hi> Hell is not <hi>parcel'd out</hi> unto the Damned, but they continually feel the <hi>whole of it.</hi> This is terrible; there is not the leaſt part of the puniſhment, that ever they are exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from undergoing: out 'tis much more terrible, that their Suffering muſt be <hi>always,</hi> and never have a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Divines have ſtretch'd their Wits to repreſent Eternity, that apprehenſions of it might be more ſuitable and affecting, but were never able to reach it. We can no more comprehend Eternity, than a Nut-ſhell can contain the whole Ocean. Suppoſe that all this World were fill'd with <hi>Sand,</hi> from the Earths Centre round, and up to the <hi>higheſt Heaven;</hi> and <hi>once</hi> in a <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> one <hi>ſingle Sand</hi> ſhould be taken away: How ſad would it be to lye in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till the <hi>whole vnst heap</hi> were gone! But after ſo many Millions and Millions of Years, for the Damned to be every whit <hi>as far from the End of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66016:27"/> their Miſery,</hi> as they were the <hi>very firſt moment</hi> they began to feel it; here <hi>all words fall ſhort,</hi> and I muſt conclude in <hi>Astoniſhment!</hi> Do not think that theſe are <hi>frightful things invented</hi> by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to <hi>ſcare</hi> you into <hi>better manners.</hi> When we warn and tell you of the Eternity of Hells puniſhment, we ſpeak the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth of the Eternal God.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I am to prove the Doctrine; That <hi>they who will not turn to God, ſhall moſt certainly be turned into Hell.</hi> The Arguments to prove this, are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt ſhall be drawn from the <hi>Wrath of God.</hi> This is <hi>revealed from Heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouneſs of Men,</hi> Rom. 1. 18. They that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to turn, and yet refuſe, that Wrath abides upon them ſtill; unbelief and impenitency bindes, as it were all their Sins faſt upon them, and they muſt needs remain under Wrath alſo, <hi>Joh. 3. ult. He that believeth not the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Nay, Wrath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being appeaſed, is increaſed, by contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Goſpel-offer of Gods favour and mercy in Chriſt. And where will unpacified Wrath at length iſſue? See <hi>Deut. 32. 22. A Fire is kindled in mine Anger, and it ſhall burn to the loweſt Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Argument ſhall be drawn from the <hi>Truth of God.</hi> He has threatned Hell for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of unconverted Sinners, <hi>Pſal. 9. 17. The Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that forget God:</hi> Let there be never ſo many of them, Hell has room enough to hold them, and their multitude will not be any Security. The Truth of God is engaged to make good <hi>all his promiſes</hi> to the Faithful, and alſo <hi>all his threatnings</hi> to the Wicked
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66016:27"/> A man muſt believe the Promiſes in order to the accompliſhment of them: But tho the Threatnings are dis-believed, they will be fulfilled; and the <hi>greater</hi> the unbelief, the <hi>more certainly</hi> and <hi>ſorely</hi> will they overtake, and lay hold on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord is to be credited when he ſpeaks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a God that <hi>cannot Lye;</hi> but when he adds his <hi>Oath</hi> to his word, what he ſayes is the <hi>more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to be aſſented to. His <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by an Oath, and when <hi>he could Swear by no greater, he Swore by himſelf.</hi> And his Oath alſo confirms his <hi>Threatnings of Wrath,</hi> Heb. 3. 18, 19. <hi>And to whom Swear he that they ſhould not enter into his Reſt, but to them that believed not? So we ſee that they could not enter in becauſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Argument to prove, that unconver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sinners ſhall be turned into Hell, ſhall be drawn <hi>from their preſent Impunity.</hi> Eſcaping now ſcot-free, we may conclude the greater certainty of a future reckoning. They that will not turn to God, we ſee that many of them are in Health, at eaſe, enjoy peace and plenty, and Sentence againſt their evil works being not <hi>now</hi> executed, and they hereupon being fully ſet to do Evil; 'tis reaſonable to believe there will be, and 'tis very Righteous there ſhould be a terrible Sentence of Condemnation, and that Sentence put in Execution upon them in the other World.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They that will not turn to God at the Goſpel call, ſhall be turned into Hell, for <hi>they ſlight the only Saviour.</hi> Chriſt calls himſelf a <hi>Door;</hi> ſo he <hi>has been,</hi> from the beginning of the World; ſo he <hi>will be</hi> to the End of it. There is <hi>no Door</hi> through which <hi>Hell</hi> can be <hi>eſcaped,</hi> but this. Unconverted Sinners <hi>wil not come to Him that they may have Life,</hi> Joh. 5. 42
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66016:28"/> therefore they are unavoidably Siezed by eternal Death. <hi>Corruptible things, as Silver and Gold,</hi> they know how to value, but the <hi>precious Blood of Chriſt</hi> is not prized, and not being Sprinkled with the Blood of Chriſt <hi>our Paſſover, who was Sacrificed for us;</hi> the Deſtroyer has power over them, and they fall into eternal Predition.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I am to vindicate the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God in thus dealing with, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally puniſhing them that will not turn to Him: And here,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the <hi>Majeſty and greatneſs of God</hi> be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, <hi>againſt whom all Sin is committed.</hi> How much greater a Crime is it to ſtrike a Prince upon the Throne, than to ſtrike a Peaſant! How much is Sin <hi>gratned,</hi> being committed againſt the <hi>Higheſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of all,</hi> who is infinitely Superiour to all other Powers, <hi>Pſal. 104. 1. O Lord, my God, thou art ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, thou art Cloathed with Honour and with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty!</hi> Pſal. 145. <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed, and his greatneſs is unſearchable.</hi> Sin is a Tranſgreſſion of a Law, enacted by the King of Heaven; and is indeed a diſowning of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Authority, as if he had no right to rule the Sinner. Think of the <hi>infinite diſtance</hi> between the <hi>God</hi> who is <hi>offended,</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> that is the <hi>Offender,</hi> and how <hi>much</hi> Sin <hi>offends;</hi> for it diſowns his <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſtrikes at his very <hi>Being;</hi> for the Sinner <hi>wiſhes</hi> there were <hi>no God</hi> to be ſubject to. I ſay, think of all this, and you will perceive that Sin deſerves everlaſting Puniſhment. The carnal Mind thinks Hell <hi>too much</hi> for a Sinner to feel, becauſe it <hi>meaſures God</hi> by it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and thinks <hi>too little</hi> of the Glorious <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:66016:28"/>2. Sinners can <hi>never by all that they ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſatisfie for their Iniquities;</hi> therefore their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in Hell is juſtly endleſs: No <hi>meer Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> can make ſatisfaction for Sin. If Chriſt the Mediatour, had not been over all <hi>God bleſſed for ever,</hi> by his Death and all his Sufferings, he would never have <hi>made Peace.</hi> His <hi>God-head</hi> put a <hi>real</hi> and <hi>infinite value</hi> upon the <hi>price</hi> he <hi>paid,</hi> and made it <hi>ſufficient</hi> for our Redemption. The Damned in Hell cannot ſatisfie the Juſtice of God for their Tranſgreſſions; therefore they juſtly are kept eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Priſoners there. It is above <hi>five Thouſand Years ago,</hi> that the <hi>Evil Angels</hi> were caſt down to Hell; by the puniſhment they have undergone, have <hi>they made any Satisfaction</hi> for their offences? No, no, ſtill they have continued in their Enmity, and deſerved more puniſhment. And from Satans utter alienation from God and all goodneſs, we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that Hell is not a place to mend any; but Sin is hight'ned; thoſe that were had on Earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe in Hell, and are unalterably confirm'd in Evil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The puniſhment of Sin in Hell is juſtly Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, becauſe Sin is <hi>inſatiable.</hi> Suppoſe a Sinner could live in this World to Eternity, there is corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enough in his Nature, to make him an <hi>Offender of God unto Eternity.</hi> If he were an <hi>everlaſting Liver</hi> upon Earth, he would be an everlaſting Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour. If the Carnal Heart would but ſpeak out, that would be its Language: <hi>I would deſire no other, no greater happineſs, than that I might live here for ever, that I might Sin here for ever.</hi> This inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Nature of Sin, this inclination and deſire of the Sinner, is known to the Heart-ſearcher; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the puniſhment he inflicts is very Righteous, tho 'tis everlaſting.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:66016:29"/>4. For the Vindication of the Righteouſneſs of God, take notice <hi>what has been offered unto Sinners, and rejected. Chriſt</hi> is offered; his juſtifying <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> his <hi>unſearchable Riches;</hi> all <hi>his Fulneſs;</hi> all the Benefits which he has purchaſed at ſo dear a Price, and yet the offer is made light of. How much is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, when Chriſt is Contemn'd! and how much of Sin is there in the Contempt! The bleſſed God in the Glorious Goſpel, does call to Sinners to turn to him; and what does he offer? His own all-ſufficient-ſelf. <hi>I my ſelf am yours, if you will turn to me, and become ſincerely mine. I will be a God to you, all my attributes ſhall be for you: I will be your Shield, and your exceeding great Reward, and your Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever!</hi> Now for a Sinner to turn a Deaf Ear to all this, is ſuch a Sin, as does deſerve the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal loſs</hi> of what is offer'd; and the feeling of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Wrath is juſt, ſince ſuch infinite and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goodneſs has been deſpiſed. I might alſo add, that the Sinner is <hi>told of this Eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before-hand;</hi> therefore if his Luſts are ſo dear, that he will venture to be Damned, rather than part with them, when thoſe Luſts that War againſt his Soul have quite undone him, and brought him down to Hell indeed, he cannot charge God with Injuſtice; but he muſt blame himſelf, becauſe when warned of Hell and Wrath, he would not fear and Flee from it.</p>
            <p>I come now to the <hi>Applacation.</hi> I begin with ſome Inferences, that may be drawn from the Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If Sinners that will not turn, ſhall be brought down to Hell; certainly <hi>Sin is another kind of thing than is commonly imagined.</hi> Oh Sin! how much art thou
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66016:29"/> miſtaken! Thou art very little underſtood on Earth! In Heaven thou art better underſtood by Saints, and full glad they are they are quite rid of thee! In Hell thou art better underſtood by Sinners, and they muſt Groan for ever under the weight of thee! O all of you, Study Hell more, if you would know Sin more fully. Gods ſeverity towards Man for Sin, argues it a very vaſt Evil. I am perſwaded, that all the Men upon Earth, that <hi>all the Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in Heaven,</hi> ſince they cannot <hi>comprehend</hi> the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and goodneſs of God,</hi> neither can they compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>all the Evil</hi> that is in Sin: And if God alone does <hi>fully underſtand how Evil Sin is,</hi> he alone is the <hi>competent Judge</hi> what <hi>Puniſhment is due to it.</hi> O <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinful Sin!</hi> Rom. 7. 13. thou canſt not be called by ſo bad a Name, as thy own is!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn from hence the <hi>Miſery of unconverted Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> Are there none unconverted here? I wiſh there were not. Are there not many unconverted in this place? I fear there are. Seriouſly conſider in what state you are. You walk upon the <hi>Brink of Hell;</hi> you <hi>Eat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> upon the <hi>Brink of Hell;</hi> in your <hi>Shops,</hi> at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> you are ſtill upon the <hi>Brink of Hell,</hi> when you lye down at Night, you <hi>Sleep</hi> upon the <hi>Brink of Hell.</hi> Oh <hi>what Hearts</hi> are yours, that you can <hi>Sleep ſecurely!</hi> Is ſuch a perilous State to be reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in? In ſuch danger, and <hi>depths of Miſery,</hi> how ſhould you cry to the Lord for mercy, <hi>Pſal. 130. 1. Davids</hi> words are proper for a Sinner to make uſe of, <hi>Pſal. 51. 1. Have mercy upon me, O Lord, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy loving kindneſs, and according to the multitude of thy tender mercies, blot out my Tranſgreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence I infer, That they who refuſe to turn to God, are <hi>certainly beſides themſelves,</hi> elſe the broken Ciſterns would not draw them away from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66016:30"/> of living Waters; and a little gain and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, would not make them venture to lye in Flames unquenchable. God ſayes, Turn ye, turn ye! Will you turn, or will ye not? If you will, you ſhall live; if you won't, where are your Wits? You are out of them in the worſt Senſe of all. The Lord now ſayes, <hi>Turn,</hi> if ye will not hear and obey, at laſt he will ſay <hi>Depart,</hi> and that word you <hi>muſt obey,</hi> and be forced away from him into everlaſting Burnings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Shall Sinners be turned into Hell; then their <hi>Proſperity is not to be envied or admired.</hi> It has been a Cuſtom in ſome places, to grant to condemn'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, a Liberty to enjoy their Pleaſures and Delights a few days before their Execution; but alas, what did theſe ſignifie to them that were to dye a few days after? A <hi>fit Repreſentation</hi> of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Wicked! They are perhaps gaudily Cloathed, and daintily Fed, and have <hi>more than Heart could wiſh:</hi> But this proſperity is very ſhort; they ſtand in <hi>ſlippery Places,</hi> and quickly fall; <hi>they are brought to Deſtruction as in a moment, and utterly conſumed with Terrours,</hi> Pſal. 73. 18, 19. The ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do very much <hi>need</hi> our <hi>pity;</hi> but nothing that they have is <hi>worth</hi> our <hi>Envy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Hence I inferr the <hi>happineſs of ſincere Converts.</hi> Many temporal Evils may be their exerciſe at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; but Hells eternal Torments they ſhall never feel, <hi>Rom. 8. 1. There is no Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> Whatever the <hi>Times</hi> are; <hi>in Eternity,</hi> and <hi>to Eternity,</hi> it will be well with them. If Hell were Ranſack't all over, you might find Profeſſours, Preachers, Princes, Nobles there; you might find worldly Wiſe, and worldly wealthy a greatmany, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66016:30"/> not <hi>one true Convert</hi> among the <hi>whole Number.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts are reconciled to God by the Blood of Chriſt, and are ſafe and happy. Hell is a dreadful place, and has a very wide <hi>Door;</hi> but who has the <hi>Key of it?</hi> The Key is not in <hi>Satans,</hi> but in <hi>Christ's</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Rev. 1. 18. I am he that liveth, and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore,</hi> Amen, <hi>and have the Keys of Hell and of Death.</hi> He will open the Door of Death, that Converts Bodies may come out of the Grave; he will keep the door of Hell faſt ſhut, that Converts ſhall never be thrown in thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> 11. Of Exhortation. That you would all <hi>conſider more ſeriouſly,</hi> and <hi>believe more heartily</hi> this Doctrine of <hi>Hell.</hi> Often think of the <hi>loſs</hi> ſuſtained, and of the <hi>Torment</hi> felt there. It was the Advice of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Let us not fly the remembrance of Hell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we may never be Tormented there.</hi> The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving conſideration of Hells puniſhment, will have many good Effects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby the <hi>deceitfulneſs of Sin</hi> will be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The deceitfulneſs of Sin <hi>hardens you, Heb. 3. 13. Exhort one another daily, while 'tis called to day, leſt any of you be hardned through the deceitfulneſs of Sin.</hi> Sin pretends to conſult your eaſe, your ſafety, your ſatisfaction, your gain, your pleaſure: Think ſeriouſly of <hi>Hell,</hi> and all theſe will be found vain pretences. Oh how <hi>very falſe</hi> a thing is Sin! <hi>Firſt</hi> you muſt <hi>prove Hell deſirable,</hi> before you can <hi>prove</hi> that <hi>Sin</hi> is worthy to be <hi>loved</hi> and <hi>ſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Remembrance of Hell, will be a <hi>great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt the Tempter.</hi> Evil Angels are great Enemies to the good Word of God; eſpecally they are diſpleaſed at Sermons concerning <hi>Chrſt</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:66016:31"/> they are unwilling that <hi>Men</hi> ſhould know the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> Sin has brought them in danger of; unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling they ſhould hear of a <hi>Saviour and Deliverer.</hi> Think of <hi>Hell</hi> whenever you find the <hi>Devil</hi> temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. He endeavours to hide <hi>Hell</hi> from your Eyes, that he may lead you ſecure thither. Satan tells the <hi>Intemperate</hi> Man, that makes himſelf a Beaſt by exceſſive Drinking; that this is the way to Exhile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and chear his Spirits, a Remedy againſt care and ſorrow, and a means to make him merry. But he would not have the Drunkard think of <hi>Hell,</hi> nor of <hi>the dreadful Cup of</hi> Gods <hi>indignation without mixture,</hi> that will be put into his hand at the laſt day. Satan tells the defrauding, over reaching <hi>Knave,</hi> that he will be a great <hi>Gainer</hi> by his Subtlety; but he <hi>hides Hell</hi> from him, where none of his <hi>Gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> and where <hi>eternal happineſs,</hi> and an <hi>immortal Soul</hi> are <hi>lost for ever.</hi> Satan tells the <hi>filthy Wretch,</hi> of the pleaſures to be found in the embraces of the well-favoured Harlot; but this he conceals; that going <hi>to her Houſe,</hi> his <hi>Feet go down to Death,</hi> and <hi>his Steps will</hi> ſoon <hi>take hold on Hell.</hi> It would be Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in you, and in all, to ſee how <hi>Sin and Hell are joyned together.</hi> It would make the Tempter loſe his labour; if you would ever remember, that in <hi>Tempting</hi> you to Sin, he does in effect only <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade</hi> to be <hi>willing for even to be deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſerious conſideration of <hi>Hell,</hi> will <hi>quicken you to cry for Mercy.</hi> upon the <hi>Sight</hi> of <hi>Hells miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> how deſirable will <hi>Mercy</hi> be in your Eyes! You will pray for this with all <hi>Prayer.</hi> God will find you in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> in the <hi>Family,</hi> and in the <hi>Cloſet,</hi> making your ſervent Supplications; and Mercy will be your great Suit. God <hi>delights in ſhewing Mercy,</hi> Mic. 7. 18. The thoughts of Hell will
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66016:31"/> make you ſee how <hi>much you need it,</hi> and ſuch fail not to obtain it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Remembrance of Hell will <hi>contribute much to your ſtedfastneſs in Religion;</hi> 'twill <hi>fortiſie and arm you againſt the fear of Man:</hi> how little is it that the <hi>greateſt Man,</hi> that the <hi>moſt of Men</hi> can do to you? to <hi>fall into the hands of mortal Men,</hi> that can but <hi>kill the body,</hi> is <hi>no great matter;</hi> but to <hi>fall into the hands of the living God, is fearful,</hi> Heb. 10. 31. Hark what our Lord ſays, <hi>Luk. 12. 4, 5. I ſay unto you my friends, be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do; but I will forewarn you whom you ſhall fear; fear him who after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into Hell; yea, I ſay unto you, fear him:</hi> Yes, he is indeed worthy to be feared! It was a ſaying of one, <hi>Omnia ſupplicia, graviorum ſuppliciorum vincuntur formi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine;</hi> all Puniſhments are overcome by the fear of greater Puniſhments. When thou art call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth to bear Teſtimony to Chriſt and to his Truth, before a ſinful and an adulterous generation; though thou ſeeſt Wracks and Wheels, though thou ſeeſt Flames and Furnaces of ſcalding Lead, be not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at the matter; the <hi>Grace and Comfort</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of Christ</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſufficient</hi> to <hi>carry</hi> thee <hi>through theſe Pains;</hi> and theſe are <hi>nothing,</hi> compared with the <hi>Vengeance of eternal fire,</hi> which will be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that <hi>draw back unto perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> III. Of <hi>Direction:</hi> How this <hi>whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may eſcape the Damnation of Hell.</hi> I hope eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Eye</hi> is <hi>broad awake;</hi> and ſhould not every <hi>Ear be open,</hi> and every <hi>Heart exceedingly attentive,</hi> when Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections concerning <hi>this</hi> are given? The Directions are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you would eſcape Hell, <hi>think of Hell, the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66016:32"/> effect of Sin, ſo long, 'till you utterly fall out with Sin the Cauſe:</hi> Sin is the only way that leads to Hell, ſhun that way and you are ſafe: Depart from evil, and though poſſibly you may become a Prey in this World, ye Satan ſhall not make a Pery of you. If <hi>Sin had never entred into the World,</hi> none in the World would have been turned into Hell; if neither Men nor Angels had ſinn'd againſt God, there would have been no ſuch thing as Hell in being. Oh! View the <hi>Flames</hi> that are ſo <hi>furious,</hi> and that will <hi>laſt for ever,</hi> and then conſider <hi>Sin</hi> was that which <hi>kindled them,</hi> and the <hi>demerit</hi> of Sin is ſo <hi>infinitely great,</hi> that it hinders them from being <hi>ever quenched:</hi> Does thy Pride ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thee to Damnation? never be Proud more: Will thy Earthly-mindedneſs bring thee to Hell? Oh ceaſe thy <hi>loving the World, and the things that are in the World!</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15. Will any Sin that rules in thee, and that thou art willingly ſubject to, <hi>reign unto Death,</hi> and ruine thee for ever? Oh be <hi>unwilling</hi> that <hi>any Sin</hi> ſhould reign any longer; and if Sin be out <hi>of thy Will,</hi> 'tis out <hi>of the Throne:</hi> Cry with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 119. 133. <hi>Order my ſteps in thy Word, and let no Iniquity have the dominion over me.</hi> Weary you muſt be of <hi>Sins dominion,</hi> as well as fear <hi>Hells Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> You muſt not think to go to Heaven, and carry your beloved Luſts along with you thither; if you are reſolved to hold faſt theſe, you and they will go to Hell together.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you would eſcape Hell, take notice how <hi>the door of Hope is open to the very worſt of you:</hi> Thoſe that are gone far in Hells road, and are within a ſtep of the burning Lake, tis poſſible for <hi>them</hi> to be catched as <hi>firebrands out of the burning.</hi> The door is open to day, I adviſe you to enter preſently; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>aſſure you</hi> 'twill <hi>ſtand open</hi> 'till tomorrow; <hi>While
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66016:32"/> it is called to day, harden not your hearts,</hi> Heb. 3. 8. Though you are <hi>fallen by your Iniquities,</hi> yet if you will <hi>Now</hi> return to the Lord, there is hope for the very worſt of you; paſt Sins ſhall all be buried, if there be a preſent Converſion. <hi>Redemption is plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and that ſhould abundantly encourage all to Hope and Turn, <hi>Pſal. 130. 7, 8. Let I ſrael hope in the Lord, for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him there is plenteous redemption, and he ſhall redeem Iſrael from all his iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If you would eſcape Hell, <hi>you muſt be ſure to look unto Jeſus:</hi> Lord Jeſus! <hi>Turn every Eye to thee, and cauſe every Heart to open and receive thee!</hi> Thoſe that were <hi>ſtung</hi> with the <hi>fiery</hi> Serpents, liv'd notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if they <hi>lookt unto the brazen Serpent:</hi> Thoſe that are in danger of Hell, and have very well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, ſhall be delivered from it, if by Faith they look to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa. 45. 22. Look unto me, and be ye ſaved, all ye ends of the Earth:</hi> Look unto him for <hi>Pardon,</hi> look unto him for <hi>Converting, Cleanſing and Renewing Grace;</hi> look unto him to be the <hi>Author</hi> of true Faith in you, and having been the Author, to be the <hi>Finiſher of your Faith</hi> alſo, <hi>Heb. 12. 2.</hi> Chriſt was <hi>for ſaken,</hi> that you might <hi>graciouſly be received</hi> by the Lord: <hi>He</hi> was <hi>Condemn'd to dye,</hi> and <hi>ſuffer'd Death</hi> upon the Croſs, that you might be deliver'd <hi>from eternal Death and Condemnation;</hi> that this was his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is plain, <hi>Joh. 3. 16. God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him,</hi> ſhould ſcape Hell, and be brought ſafe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66016:33"/>HEB. 12. Part of <hi>v. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—And the Sin that does ſo eaſily beſet us.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the foregoing Chapter, the Apoſtle diſcourſes concerning <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the <hi>ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen:</hi> He declares at large the wonderful and glorious effects that this Faith produced in the Saints under the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: By Faith theſe Believers denyed themſelves; by Faith they Conquered the whole World, not fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its ſierceſt Perſecutions; deſpiſing all its Wealth, all its Pleaſures, all its Glory, <hi>and confeſſed they were ſtrangers and ſojourners on the Earth:</hi> By Faith they <hi>ſaw Him that is inviſible,</hi> and looked <hi>for a City that that hath foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this Verſe where my Text lies, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle applyes unto thoſe believing <hi>Hebrews</hi> to whom he writes, what he had ſpoken concerning their <hi>faithful Fore-fathers:</hi> Theſe are called a <hi>Cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes:</hi> Witneſſes they were, concerning what? tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning the <hi>Vanity</hi> of all things that are ſeen, that are but <hi>temporal:</hi> Witneſſes concerning the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of thoſe things that are not ſeen, which are <hi>eternal.</hi> They are ſtyled a <hi>Cloud,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>greatneſs of their Number;</hi> and perhaps there may be ſome alluſion to the <hi>Cloud</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> that <hi>guided Iſrael into Canaan:</hi> For though our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> was <hi>typiſied</hi> by <hi>that Cloud,</hi> and he is the <hi>unerring Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Example</hi> whom we are bound to follow; yet in Scripture we are adviſed alſo to follow <hi>the foot-ſteps of the Flock;</hi> and in this very Epiſtle, to be <hi>followers of them who through Faith and Patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her it the Promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66016:33"/>
            <p>The Courſe of a Chriſtian in this World is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a <hi>Race;</hi> this Race muſt be <hi>run,</hi> that the Prize at the end of it may be obtained; and that we may run it the better, we are <hi>removere prohibens,</hi> to remove Impediments, to lay aſide <hi>every Weight,</hi> and the <hi>Sin that does ſo eaſily beſet us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words I have read, there are three things obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is an <hi>Inimation</hi> of a <hi>Danger,</hi> and that is from <hi>Sin:</hi> Sin and Danger are inſeparable; how can it chuſe but be prejudicial to him that's guilty of it! you may as well imagine <hi>Hell</hi> to be without <hi>Pain,</hi> as <hi>Sin</hi> to be without <hi>Peril.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The greateſt danger is from the Sin that does moſt eaſily beſet us; 'tis called by the Holy Ghoſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Sin that hangs falteſt about us: Some by this underſtand <hi>Original Sin,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation and Corruption of Nature; ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the carnal and enſnaring <hi>Fear of Man:</hi> The Apoſtle arms the <hi>Hebrw</hi> Saints againſt this, and would have them couragious, and if called to it, <hi>reſiſt even to blood, ſlriving againſt ſin.</hi> But by the Sin that does moſt eaſily beſet us, we may underſtand any ſin that does ſo: Yet when we take notice of the <hi>Maſter-ſin,</hi> which is moſt apt to prevail, we ſhould by all means <hi>trace it</hi> to its <hi>Original,</hi> and take notice of the corrupt Fountain from which this ſtrong and filthy Stream proceeds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is the way how to be <hi>ſecured from Danger,</hi> by laying aſide <hi>every weight,</hi> and eſpecially the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and the <hi>heavieſt Clogg of all,</hi> the Sin that does moſt eaſily beſet us. Caſt away <hi>every tranſgreſſion, ſo iniquity ſhall not be your ruine;</hi> but eſpecially that which naturally you <hi>love beſt</hi> and <hi>more than all,</hi> becauſe <hi>this, this,</hi> is moſt of all pernicious and deſtructive.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66016:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The Doctrine which I raiſe from the words is this. <hi>Though all ſin is to be caſt away, the Maſter-ſin eſpecially is to be abandoned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Doctrine I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prove that <hi>all Sin</hi> is to be caſt away.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhew you how the <hi>Maſter ſin</hi> may be <hi>known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Produce the Reaſons, why <hi>this</hi> in a <hi>ſpecial</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is to be <hi>forſaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then in the laſt place make <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am to prove that <hi>every ſin</hi> ſhould be caſt away; and the Argument to convince you of this, is in the Verſe where my Text lies. Every Sin is a <hi>weight,</hi> and a moſt unreaſonable thing it is, that Men ſhould be fond of that which is burthenſome and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. The weightineſs of Sin, I ſhall demonſtrate in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sin is a weight to <hi>a ſoftned and ſenſible ſoul;</hi> though a ſtupid Tranſgreſſor feels Sin no more than a ſtone does a Mountain, that lies upon it; yet when once the Heart of Stone is turned into a Heart of Fleſh, Sin preſently becomes very burthenſome. He that has a <hi>new Heart and a new Spirit</hi> given him, will have <hi>new</hi> and <hi>other</hi> apprehenſions of Sin, he will look upon Sin with ſorrow, and himſelf with ſelf-abhorrency, <hi>Ezek. 36. 26, 31. A new Heart will I give you, a new Spirit will I put within you. Then ſhall ye remember your evil wayes and your doings that have not been good, and ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight for your iniquities and your abominations. David</hi> could not make light of ſin, when once convinced of its evil by the Spirit; he grieves becauſe he had offended God; he fears his wrath that he had deſerved; and earneſtly implores compaſſion and favour. His Sin lay very hard upon him, <hi>Pſal. 38. 4, 6. Mine iniquities are gone over my head,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66016:34"/> as an heavy burthen, they are too heavy for me; I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sin is a weight unto <hi>the damned in Hell:</hi> that 'tis ſo, I know; but <hi>how</hi> weighty, I cannot expreſs, no mind on Earth is able to conceive. Sin is the weight which has ſunk all the Souls that are there into that place of Wo; and becauſe ſin will ly upon them for ever, they ſhall never be able to riſe up under it. In Hell there is a full, a general, an everlaſting Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that <hi>ſin is heavy.</hi> If we could diſcourſe with the <hi>rich</hi> Man, who as the Goſpel tells us is in Hell, and <hi>ask him,</hi> whether his Gluttony, Pride, contempt of God, hatred of Holineſs, are <hi>light</hi> or <hi>weighty?</hi> Oh! <hi>what</hi> would that <hi>Tongue</hi> that cryed out for a <hi>drop of Water,</hi> anſwer to ſuch a queſtion? Surely none in Hell can make light of ſin which brought them thither.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sin is a weight which <hi>burthens the whole Creation.</hi> Hard-hearted <hi>Man groans not</hi> under it, when the <hi>whole Creation beſides</hi> does. The <hi>Creatures were made ſubject to vanity, not willingly, but by reaſon of him who hath ſubjected the ſame in hope,</hi> Rom. 8. 20. and <hi>v. 22. We know that the whole Creation groaneth and travelleth in pain toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther even until now.</hi> And all theſe travelling pains, they are the effects of Sin. <hi>Solomon</hi> in the Book of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes,</hi> uſes ſeveral very ſignificant expreſſions: <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all is vaniny;</hi> and <hi>all things are full of labour; Man cannot utter it.</hi> And again, there <hi>are many things that increaſe vanity.</hi> When Sin entred into the World it made a <hi>ſad alteration</hi> in it, well may the Creatures groan under it; and though their pains are terrible, <hi>pains of travel;</hi> yet becauſe <hi>ſuch pains,</hi> they are <hi>hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> and will iſſae in a <hi>reſtauration,</hi> which will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be, for God has ſaid it. He has told us thus much, that the <hi>Creature ſhall be delivered from the Bondage of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66016:35"/> Corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Children of God,</hi> Rom. 8. 21. But the manner of this Reſtauration, he has not told us: Gods <hi>ſilence</hi> ſhould repreſs <hi>inqut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Curioſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Sin was found a Weight <hi>by Jeſus the Mediator.</hi> He undertook (and 'twas well for us he did) to bear this Burthen, and <hi>no Shoulders</hi> but his could have born it; but when he bore it, how did he groan under it! This put him into an <hi>Agony,</hi> this made him <hi>Sweat,</hi> and Sweat <hi>drops of Blood.</hi> This made him cry out, <hi>my Soul is excceeding ſorrowful, even unto Death: And, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Oh! bleſſed Saviour, <hi>what extorted ſuch cryes as theſe from Thee?</hi> Oh! Sinner, <hi>It was thy Sin, and the Sins of all others whom I ſave, that lay ſo hard upon Me,</hi> Iſa. 53. 6. <hi>All we like Sheep,</hi> ſayes the Prophet, <hi>have gone aſtray, we have turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid upon him the Iniquity of us all.</hi> if the Man Chriſt Jeſus had not been the Eternal Son of God, he could never have born ſuch an heavy Load, as all the Sins of his whole Church laid upon him at once all together.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God <hi>himſelf complains of Sin as a weighty thing,</hi> which <hi>He</hi> is very <hi>weary of,</hi> Iſa. 43. 24. <hi>Thou haſt made me to ſerve with thy Sins, and haſt wearied me with thine Iniquities.</hi> And, Amos 2. 13. <hi>Behold I am preſſed under you, as a Cart is preſſed that is full of Sheaves.</hi> Sin is a Burthen to the Almighty, tho he be ſo rich and abundant in Forbearance and Long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering. Nay, Sin will make <hi>Duties</hi> to be a Burthen to Him, <hi>Iſa. 1. 13, 14. Bring no more vain Oblations, your Sabbaths and calling of Aſſemblies, I cannot away with, it is Iniquity even the Solemn Meeting. Your new Moons, and your appointed Feasts, my Soul hateth; they are a Trouble to me, I am weary to bear them.</hi> And 'tis obſervable, when the Lord comes to a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66016:35"/> to <hi>puniſh</hi> Sinners, becauſe of their Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, He ſpeaks as One about to <hi>eaſe himſelf</hi> of a <hi>Load</hi> Iſa. 1. 24. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, the mighty one of Iſrael: Ah! I will eaſe me of my Adverſaries, and avenge me of my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> If Sin be thus a Weight, I adviſe all to be weary, and beg to be eaſed of it. He is a ſenſeleſs Fool indeed, who makes a Mock of Sin, and ſtill goes on to add unto his own Burthen.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place. I ſhall ſhew you <hi>how the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sin may be known:</hi> And here I would premiſe theſe three things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. All Sin that is <hi>allowed of,</hi> may truly be ſaid <hi>to Reign,</hi> where 'tis allowed. A Man that wilfully continues in the Commiſſion of any Sin, is certainly the Servant of it, whatever it be. 'Tis the Miſery of the unregenerate, that they have, <hi>tot Dominos quot vitia,</hi> ſo many <hi>Luſts,</hi> ſo many <hi>Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is in many Perſons a <hi>particular</hi> Sin, <hi>which does prevail more than any other.</hi> In the Natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy there are all the Humours, yet <hi>One</hi> commonly is <hi>Predominant,</hi> and the Denomination is from <hi>that.</hi> Thus 'tis in the Body of Sin; tho there is a Maſs of all Corruption; yet there may be ſome ſpecial Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that has the greateſt ſtrength and preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. This in Scripture is called, the <hi>ſweet</hi> Sin, in which the greateſt delight is taken, compared to a <hi>ſweet Morſel</hi> under the Tongue, <hi>Job 20. 12, 13. Tho wickedneſs is ſweet in his Mouth, tho he hide it under his Tongue, tho he ſpare it and forſake it not;</hi> yet at laſt it proves extremely bitter, deadly as the <hi>very Gall of Aſps within him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There are ſome in whom <hi>ſeveral Sins are ſo Predominant,</hi> that 'tis hard to determine which is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66016:36"/> 
               <hi>most Maſter.</hi> Some have ſo <hi>hot</hi> an <hi>Anger,</hi> and ſo <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>furious</hi> a <hi>Luſt,</hi> that you cannot ſo eaſily judge, which of theſe is hotteſt. Nay, in ſome, Sins that ſeem very <hi>contrary</hi> one to another, yet in ſeveral reſpects they will both prevail. Many a Man is liberal and <hi>profuſe,</hi> as to his <hi>Ornaments</hi> and <hi>Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> he ſpends freely in the Sumptuous furniſhing of his Table; Hand and Purſe are open, if he be in <hi>Riotous Company.</hi> Yet if you ask this Man but for a <hi>lutle,</hi> to a <hi>good uſe:</hi> Tell him that the <hi>Members of Chriſt</hi> are many of them very <hi>needy;</hi> and that he who <hi>gives to the Poor, lends unto the Lord;</hi> here he is ſtrangely <hi>Covetous</hi> and <hi>cloſe Fiſled.</hi> Theſe things premiſed, I ſhall <hi>diſcover</hi> the <hi>Maſter Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That is a Maſter Sin, unto which the <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion does moſt ſtrongly incline.</hi> They that are of a <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine</hi> Complexion, are inclined to Laſciviouſneſs, Voluptuouſneſs, and an aiery frothineſs of Spirit, which a great hinderance unto ſerious Impreſſions. In the <hi>Cholerick</hi> Paſſion and Anger are apt to prevail, and to hurry them to revengeful words and Actions; not conſidering what injury they do to others, and how much more to themſelves. The <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick</hi> are prone to Envy, Malice, Diſcontent: The <hi>Flegmatick.</hi> unto Stupidity, Careleſneſs and Sloth. Now Satan takes notice of the Complexion, ſails with the Stream of it, and ſuits his Bait to it; and hereby has very great advantage. Tho <hi>no ſin</hi> has the <hi>Dominion</hi> in Believers; for they <hi>are not under the Law, but under Grace,</hi> Rom. 6. 14. yet the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion Sin is apt ſometimes to <hi>maſter</hi> even them alſo; therefore they had need to be watchful againſt it, and to take great care and pains to mortify it. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves his own Conſtitution, and makes conſcience of keeping under his Body that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66016:36"/> his Temperament might not be his Temptation, <hi>1 Cor. 9. ult. I keep under my bring it into ſubjection, leſt by any means, when I have Preached unto others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That is a Maſter-ſin, unto which your <hi>Callings and Conditions make you most liable.</hi> They that <hi>trade</hi> in the World, how apt are they through the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their own Hearts, to defraud and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach; to get immoderate and diſhoneſt gain: hence that ſtrict Prohibition, <hi>1 Theſ. 4. 6. Let no man go beyond or defraud his Brother in any matter, knowing that the Lord is the Avenger of all ſuch, as we alſo have forewarned you, and testified.</hi> How apt are they, to venture upon the Sin of Lying and Equivocation, for advantage, and they teach and command their Servants and Children to follow their pernicious Examples; as if Earthly gain were ſo conſiderable, that 'tis no great matter how many Souls are loſt for the ſake of it. They that are <hi>Rich in this World,</hi> are prone to be <hi>high-minded, and to trust in uncertain Riches,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 17. to withhold <hi>the Hire from the</hi> poor Labourers; to live in <hi>wantonneſs and pleaſure,</hi> Jam. 5. 1, 2, 3. to <hi>be full and deny God, and ſay, Who is the Lord?</hi> They that are poor in the World, are prone to <hi>Steal;</hi> (all unjuſt dealing, is Stealing, an unjuſt action makes a Man a Thief in Gods account) and <hi>to take the Name of God in vain,</hi> Prov. 30. 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That is a Maſter-ſin, which the Sinner is moſt <hi>unwilling ſhould be brought to light, and cannot bear to be reproved for.</hi> We read, <hi>Joh. 3. 20. Every one that doth Evil, hateth the Light, neither cometh to the Light, lest his Deeds ſhould be reproved;</hi> but of all others, he cannot endure to be reproved for the Sin that eaſily beſets him, and that he loves moſt. He <hi>tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples the Pearl</hi> of reproof <hi>under his Feet,</hi> and is read
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66016:37"/> to turn again, and <hi>rend</hi> the reprover. <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt was a <hi>burning and a ſhining Light. Herod</hi> the King heard him, ſome of his Exhortaions and Doctrines went down with <hi>Herod,</hi> and produced a partial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. At length the Baptiſt comes home, and ſtrikes at the Maſter Sin, tells <hi>Herod</hi> of his <hi>Herodias,</hi> and that it was <hi>not lawful for him to have his Brothers Wife.</hi> This was not to be born, the King counted the Prophet <hi>too bold</hi> to meddle with <hi>his beloved Lust.</hi> He hears him no longer, he ſuffers him to Preach to others no longer. He firſt puts him into Priſon, and afterwards puts him to Death, and thus was this burning and ſhining Light extinguiſhed, <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. 17,-27.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Maſter Sin, <hi>Conſcience when awakened by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, is very apt to accuſe the Sinner of, and furiouſly to fly in his face for.</hi> Conſcience though it ſleeps in a Calm, uſually awakes in a Storm; when Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threatning Affliction lies hard upon the Sinner, and he looks beyond Death unto Judgment, and into Eternity; then Conſcience ſpeaks plainly; rebukes boldly, and eſpecially the Maſter-Sin makes it very clamorous. <hi>Envy</hi> was a Sin <hi>Predominant</hi> in <hi>Joſephs Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> they could not bear the thoughts of his future advancement; they ſold him a Slave, to prevent his being exalted over them, as was preſignified by his Dreams. Many years after, God calls for a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon the Land; down go theſe Brethren into <hi>Egypt</hi> to buy Food, there <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſeizes them, deals hardly with them, and they are in great Diſtreſs. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience now awakes, with great terrour flies in their Faces; and their envy and cruel dealing with <hi>Joſeph</hi> their Brother, comes to remembrance with great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and trouble, <hi>Gen. 42. 21, 22. They ſaid one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our Brother; in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66016:37"/> that we ſaw the anguiſh of his Soul, when he beſought us and we would not hear; therefore is this diſtreſs come upon us, therefore behold alſo is his blood required.</hi> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence does Comment upon Affliction, and has its <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible gloſſes.</hi> Theſe <hi>blows</hi> are given thee for thy <hi>ſecret filthineſs,</hi> for thy <hi>intemperance,</hi> for thy <hi>injuſtice,</hi> for thy <hi>earthlimindedneſs,</hi> for thy <hi>doing the Work of God Heartleſly and negligently!</hi> Obſerve what Conſcience <hi>now</hi> ſays, for the Maſter Sin it takes ſpecial notice of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That is a Maſter Sin, which <hi>when the Sinner is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most perſwaded to be a Convert, hinders him from being a Convert altogether.</hi> That <hi>Jacob</hi> might have Corn, he was contented that ten of his Sons ſhould go and fetcht it; but how loath was he to let <hi>Benjamin go!</hi> When a Sinner is convinced of the neceſſity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, he may conſent to part with <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> or <hi>ten</hi> Sins; but that which is moſt beloved, he huggs ſtill, <hi>that Sin</hi> and <hi>he</hi> muſt never part. When the Sould is ready to be <hi>eſpouſed</hi> to Chriſt. <hi>This</hi> Sin ſtands up and <hi>forbids the Banes.</hi> We read of a young man in the Goſpel, ſoberly inclined; he ſaw the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of eternal Life and the value of it; he comes to Jeſus, and ſays, <hi>Good Master, What ſhall I do that I may inherit eternal Life?</hi> Our Lord tells him of the <hi>commands,</hi> the young man is glad of this, for as to the letter of the ſecond-Table-precepts; he had been a ſtrict obſerver of them all from his Youth up. At length our Lord, who knew <hi>Love to the World</hi> was his Maſter Sin; bids him <hi>to go and ſell all that he had on Earth,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> him, and he ſhould have a more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during and better <hi>Treaſure in Heaven.</hi> But his Love to the World hindred his Believing and Converſion, he goes away <hi>very ſorrowful, for he was very rich,</hi> Mat. 19. 21, 22. His Riches were very unreaſonably and exceſſively loved, he cleaves to Mammon, and leaves the only Saviour!</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:66016:38"/>6. That is a Maſter Sin, which <hi>pretends most highly to conſult the Sinners ſafety, gain, and pleaſure.</hi> To be ſafe, to be advantaged, and delighted, are things very taking to Humane Nature; pretences this way are prevalent, but all Sins pretences are vain. When our Lord commands that the <hi>right eye</hi> ſhould be <hi>pluckt out,</hi> the <hi>right hand cut off;</hi> the meaning is not, that Chriſtianity binds us cruelly to diſmember our ſelves: Indeed the abuſe of our members is ſeverely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, but our members themſelves are not to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, but employed after an holy manner. That therefore which our Lord intends is this, either, that we ſhould be <hi>as without an eye,</hi> to behold vanity and tempting Objects; as <hi>without an hand</hi> to work that which is evil. Or, that though Sin be naturally as dear to us as our right eye; as ſeemingly neceſſary as our right hand; yet we muſt part with it, and not ſpare it to the hazard ruine of our ſelves for ever, <hi>Mat. 5. 29, 30.</hi> I might alſo add, that Sinners are apt above all to <hi>wiſh,</hi> that the Maſter Sin were <hi>no Sin</hi> at all. And becauſe the Law forbids it, they hate the Law; and the motions of their wicked Hearts towards it are more ſtrong and violent. And here is a notable difference between an <hi>unſanctified,</hi> and a <hi>ſanctified</hi> Heart. The unſanctified Heart wiſhes that the Law were <hi>leſs Holy,</hi> that <hi>Sins</hi> were <hi>no Sins;</hi> but the Heart that is ſanctified, does not deſire the Law were <hi>leſs ſtrict and pure,</hi> but that <hi>it ſelf</hi> were <hi>more pure,</hi> and more conformed unto a Law that is ſo good and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent; it does not deſire a Liberty to commit Sin, but that all the remaining Juſtings of the Fleſh that way, were more throughly mortified.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I am to produce the <hi>Reaſons</hi> why this Maſter Sin ought <hi>eſpecially to be abandoned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:66016:38"/>1. Becauſe, this is <hi>Gods Principal Enemy.</hi> All Sin is againſt him, but <hi>this</hi> is a ſpecial Provocation in the the eyes of his Holineſs and Glory. The Apoſtle tells us that <hi>Love</hi> is the <hi>greateſt Grace;</hi> and Chriſt himſelf ſays, that Love is the <hi>firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> The Maſter Sin, which is moſt beloved, which takes away the affection of the Heart, which God chiefly requires; muſt needs provoke Him unto great Jealouſie. This is the <hi>Preſumptuous Sin,</hi> 'tis greatly offenſive, for deſervedly 'tis called the <hi>great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> Pſal. 19. 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Maſter Sin ſhould be abandon'd, becauſe in a ſpecial manner <hi>it ſeparates between God, and the Soul that is guilty of it.</hi> Sin has many bad effects, but a worſe can't be named than this, <hi>Iſa. 59. 2. Your iniquities have ſeparated between you and your God, and your ſins have hid his face from you that he will not hear.</hi> Let the <hi>Saints in Heaven</hi> ſpeak what 'tis to ſee the <hi>Face of God!</hi> Oh the <hi>evil</hi> that is in Sin, which cauſes the Face of God to be <hi>hid</hi> from the Sinner! Every Sin may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a cloud; but the Sin which does moſt eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet us, is the blackeſt, the darkeſt cloud of all, which does moſt totally deprive us of the Light of Gods Countenance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Maſter-Sin be not abandon'd, <hi>no other Sin whatſoever, can be truly repented of.</hi> A man may indeed <hi>abſtain</hi> from ſome Sins, but he does not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from them, <hi>as Sins,</hi> and becauſe they are <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing</hi> to God; becauſe contrary to his will, and becauſe they hinder Communion with God; if he did, then certainly he would keep himſelf from the <hi>belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sin,</hi> which is principally hateful to God, and the grand obſtruction of fellowſhip with Him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Maſter Sin ſhould be abandon'd, becauſe this is <hi>ſo great a grief unto the Holy Spirit of God.</hi> How
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66016:39"/> often does he tell the falſe Profeſſour of his lying Tongue! and the unjuſt Profeſſour of his unrighteous dealing! The good Spirit vouchſafes to ſtrive with very wicked men, and moves them to hate the Sin which they unreaſonably Love to their own ruine. But if Sin be loved ſtill, the Spirit is grieved and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And is it ſafe to grieve and vex the Sanctifier, the Comforter? No. Read what follows upon vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit, <hi>Iſa. 63. 10. But they rebelled, and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Holy Spirit, therefore he was turned to be their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and he fought againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Maſter Sin ſhould be abandon'd, becauſe 'tis <hi>this chiefly that keeps the Lord Jeſus our of the Throne.</hi> Why do ſo many ſay in their Hearts, <hi>we will not have Chriſt to Reign over us?</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe they are reſolved their <hi>fleſhly</hi> and their <hi>wordly Lusts</hi> ſhall rule there ſtill. And if Chriſt <hi>rule</hi> not, 'tis in <hi>vain</hi> to expect he will <hi>ſave,</hi> for he is the <hi>Author of Eternal Salvation unto them that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5. 9. Nay, as he will <hi>not ſave</hi> them that will not be ſubject to him, ſo he has threatned to <hi>ſlay</hi> them. As <hi>for thoſe mine Enemies, that would not I ſhould reign over them, bring them forth, and ſlay them before me,</hi> Luk. 19. 27.</p>
            <p>I come in the laſt place to the <hi>Application,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> are theſe three.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> I. By way of <hi>Examination:</hi> Try your ſelves, whether you are willing to abandon the Sin that does ſo eaſily beſet you: and for you your help in this matter, I would ask you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are you willing <hi>to have this Sin, whatever it be, diſcover'd?</hi> Are you willing that God ſhould ſignifie to you, what 'tis in <hi>you</hi> that <hi>moſt of all diſpleaſes</hi> him? <hi>Job</hi> profeſſes that he <hi>cover'd not his Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Adam, by hiding his Iniquity in his Boſom,</hi> Job.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66016:39"/> 31. 33. He that <hi>hides</hi> Sin, <hi>loves</hi> it; he that pleads for Sin, is a Servant, a Slave to it. The <hi>defence</hi> of Sin, is worſe than the <hi>Offence</hi> it ſelf. Can you come to God, and ſay, <hi>Lord!</hi> I open my Heart to Thee. <hi>Search, Ranſack here; Let no ſin lye concealed! Let not ſo much as</hi> one <hi>be ſpared, but eſpecially diſcover the</hi> Maſter-ſin, <hi>which is my greateſt Enemy, as well as thine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Are you willing to <hi>hear all the Evil the Word does ſpeak againſt the Maſter-ſin?</hi> If ſo, this would argue that 'tis no longer loved. 'Tis a Sign of malice towards our Neighbour, if we are glad to hear all the Evil that is ſpoken of him, and all the Reproach that is caſt upon him. 'Tis a Sign of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to Sin, when we like to have it diſcovered, when we like that its deceitful and damnable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould be repreſented, and the falſneſs, foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and filthineſs of it ſhould be laid open and naked. Sin is ſo great an Evil, that there cannot be too much Evil ſpoken of it; 'tis ſo great an Enemy, that you can never too faithfully and plainly be warned againſt it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do you apprehend your <hi>greateſt danger to be from your Maſter Sin?</hi> and therefore continually endeavour the Mortification of it? The King of <hi>Syria</hi> give this Commiſſion to his Army, <hi>Fight neither againſt ſmall nor great, ſave onely with the King of Iſrael.</hi> What? were all beſides to be ſpared? No certainly, many <hi>Iſrael.</hi> fell in the battel: But there was a principal deſign to <hi>take</hi> at leaſt, if not to <hi>cut off</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael. All Sin</hi> deſerves thy hatred, <hi>no Sin is</hi> ſo <hi>ſmall</hi> an Enemy as that thou mayeſt <hi>ſafely ſpare it.</hi> But the Maſter Sin is the <hi>chief foe,</hi> therefore <hi>its</hi> deſtruction ſhould chiefly be deſigned. That Man that is an Enemy to his Maſter Sin deſires it may be ſtill weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by all means. Oh! faith he, that every <hi>Mercy</hi> may help to kill it! leading me to Repentance for it! That every ſtroke of the <hi>Roa</hi> may help to ſtrike it more dead! that every <hi>Sermon</hi> may give this Sin a blow! that by every <hi>Prayer</hi> I may obtain more ſtrength againſt it! That every time I come to the <hi>Table of the Lord, this Sin</hi> may be in a greater meaſure Crucified!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE II</hi> Of <hi>Exhortation.</hi> And of this there are two Branches.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:66016:40"/>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to <hi>Sinners,</hi> that are under the <hi>full Power</hi> of their Maſter Sin.</p>
            <p>Then I ſhall ſpeak to <hi>Saints,</hi> in whom there are too great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I am to ſpeak <hi>to Sinners</hi> who are under the <hi>full Power</hi> of their Maſter Sin. It is ſtoried concerning <hi>Agrippina</hi> the Mother of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Coeſar,</hi> that it was told her by an Oracle, that her Son ſhould be Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> but afterwards ſhould kill his own Mother. <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina</hi> replies, <hi>Occidat, mode imperet!</hi> Let him kill <hi>me,</hi> ſo <hi>he</hi> does but reion. O 'tis the Language of all preſumptuous Sinners concerning their Maſter Luſts, <hi>Let them but reign, no matter though they are our Damnation and Deſtruction!</hi> But what do you ſee in Sin, or in its Wages, that any of you ſhould be thus fond of its Service? What good reaſon can be given, why Sin ſhould have <hi>one ſlave</hi> in this whole <hi>Congregation?</hi> or in the <hi>whole World?</hi> I earneſtly exhort you to lay aſide <hi>every weight,</hi> but eſpecially the <hi>Sin that does moſt eaſily beſet you.</hi> Arguments to perſwade are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, the <hi>Maſter Sin is the ſtrongeſt hold of Satan.</hi> While Sin keeps up its Dominion, Satan holds faſt his Poſſeſſion. This Sin is your moſt deadly diſeaſe, and the ſtrongeſt Cord, in which the Devil binds you and leads you Captive at his Pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Maſter Sin is the <hi>great hindrance of the efficacy of the means of Grace.</hi> This makes the Preachers pains, loſt labour; this makes Mercies and Afflictions to be loſt upon you; this makes you to loſe all the duties you perform.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Maſter Sin is <hi>not without its Train.</hi> A great Perſon, eſpecially a <hi>Crown'd Head,</hi> is not without a great many that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him! A Maſter Sin has a <hi>great Attendance:</hi> Many luſts are ſubſervient to this <hi>Main</hi> one, that the greater and more plentiful Proviſion may be made for the fulfilling it. How great is thy dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger who haſt many Enemies lodging in thee, and lording it over thee!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Suppoſe, this Maſter Sin <hi>were alone, this were enough to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine thee.</hi> If a Piſtol is diſcharged at the Heart, and a ſmall Bullet enter there; it kills as certainly as if there were a thouſand Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons diſcharged at a man at once. One Sin ſuffered to rule in thy Heart is ſufficient were there no more, effectually and eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ruine thee.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Maſter Sin <hi>wars againſt thy Soul moſt dangerouſly, and wounds moſt deeply.</hi> And after it has ruined thee, Oh with what anguiſh will it be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lected on in the loweſt Hell! This will be there thy heavieſt load! Thou wilt remem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er how deaf thou were to all Counſel to caſt it away, and how great thy madneſs was, in taking <hi>moſt pleaſure</hi> in <hi>that,</hi> which proves the cauie of the <hi>greateſt,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:66016:40"/> even everlaſting <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Vexation.</hi> Oh be ſo wiſe, as to change your old Maſter, Sin; and let Chriſt become your Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am to ſpeak <hi>to Saints,</hi> in whom there are <hi>too great remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the <hi>Sin</hi> that was <hi>once</hi> their <hi>Maſter.</hi> I exhort you <hi>more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually and throughly to mortifie it.</hi> Pray conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If this Sin does frequently prevail, it will <hi>keep you very low in Grace.</hi> Faith will be weak, Hope will be dampt, Love will be cool; and the whole inward Man will wofully languiſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As you will be weak in Grace, ſo will be <hi>low in Comfort.</hi> When Temptations are yielded to, Conſcience will be diſquieted, Peace will be diſturbed; Thy Pride, thy Paſſion, thy carnal Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions prevailing, will make thy Heart <hi>too much like the troubled Sea when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt forth mire and dirt,</hi> Iſa. 57. 20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Prevalency of this eaſily beſetting Sin, will <hi>binder you from being ſo ſerviceable to your great and gracious Lord.</hi> It will make his work to be neglected; and when done, to be done too negligently: <hi>ſorry Servants</hi> you will be, and <hi>very ſorry</hi> your <hi>ſervices</hi> will be. The <hi>more ſanctified</hi> you are, the <hi>fitter</hi> you are for your <hi>Maſters uſe, 2 Tim. 2, 21.</hi> but Sin makes you unmeet, and more unable and unwilling to ſerve him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Sin will make you to <hi>ſhine leſs in your lives;</hi> 'twil fully your Converſations, and hinder you from adorning the Goſpel. Oh keep unſpotted, and walk exactly as in the day; that you <hi>may be blameleſs and harmleſs the Children ó God without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Nation, and that you may ſhine as Lights in the World,</hi> Phil. 2. 15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This Sin may cauſe <hi>you to ſet in a Cloud.</hi> It may fill you with <hi>doubts</hi> when you are <hi>dying,</hi> and that will be very dreadful. You may be terribly frighted with the fears of Hell, when you are juſt at Heavens gate. Be therefore upright, keep your ſelves from the iniquity that does moſt eaſily beſet you; that you may be more uſeful in your lives, have the ſtronger and more lively hope in Death; and that your End when it comes may be more perfect Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE III.</hi> Of <hi>Direction:</hi> How the <hi>Sin which does moſt eaſily beſet you, may be laid aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Pray for <hi>a clean Heart,</hi> Pſal. 51. 10. <hi>David</hi> having been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by a ſtrong Corruption, and done a Deed that was very foul, cryes for a purer Heart, a more right and conſtant Spirit; he knew that to <hi>purge the Fountain,</hi> was the way to have the <hi>ſtreams clean:</hi> Go unto God for <hi>a new Heart,</hi> which he has promiſed, and will give to <hi>all</hi> who <hi>prize and deſire</hi> ſuch an Heart. Strike at the <hi>root</hi> of in the Heart, then the branches, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>top branch,</hi> the Maſter-ſin will wither.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:66016:41"/>2. Seriouſly lay to Heart, how <hi>much he Sin that naturally is moſt beloved, does deſerve your hatred:</hi> Hated Sin is ſo <hi>weak,</hi> that it can ruine none; 'tis the love of Sin that gives it power, and as it were puts a Sword into its hand ſlay you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſiſt the <hi>very firſt ſtirrings of this Sin in you:</hi> I believe if, <hi>David</hi> asſoon as ever he beheld from his Palace the beauteous <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> had preſently turn'd away his eyes, and had fallen upon his knees, and gone to Prayer, he had overcome the Temptation. Sin is more weak at the beginning: Our Lords Counſel is, <hi>Watch and Pray, that ye</hi> enter <hi>not into temptation,</hi> Mat. 26. 41.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If you would abandon the Maſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-ſin, <hi>Pray much for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Grace:</hi> Is Pride thy Maſter-ſin? Pray much for Humility; Is Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n thy Maſter-ſin? Pray much for P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tience, and for the Meekneſs and Gentleneſs of Chriſt: Is Love to the World thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſin? Pray that thou may'ſt riſe with Chriſt, and love, and mind a better World; better Honours, better Pleaſures, a more laſting Wealth than this World can yield.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let the <hi>Word of God, which does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rbid and threaten this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſin, be carefully hid in your Heart:</hi> This Word may be in thy <hi>Mouth,</hi> thou mayeſt talk of it; it may be in thy <hi>Mind,</hi> thou may'ſt have a national Knowledge of it: Nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t may go further, and be in thy <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and be thought of in the very act of Sin. But if it will be in thy Heart, if thy <hi>Will and Affections</hi> are taken with it, then it will be an effectual Preſervative againſt Iniquity, <hi>Pſal. 119. 11. Thy Word have I hid in my Heart, that I might not ſin againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Improve <hi>the Death of our Lord Jeſus:</hi> Bring the Sin which does ſo eaſily beſet you to the <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt. No Sin <hi>truly dyis</hi> but upon <hi>Chriſts Croſs,</hi> Gal 5. 24. <hi>They that are Chriſts, have Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the fleſh with the affections and luſts;</hi> theſe are never Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by being <hi>Crucified.</hi> How can the <hi>old Adam</hi> dye, but upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Adam?</hi> Rom. 6. 6. <hi>Knowing this, that our old man is Crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Call in the <hi>Spirits aid:</hi> He can make the Word <hi>ſharp as a two-edged Sword</hi> to pierce the Heart, and to ſlay the ſtrongeſt Sin there: He glorifies Chriſt, and can draw you to him, and enable you by Faith to derive Grace from him, ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to help you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt powerful Corruptions: He can kill the Sin that is hardeſt to be ſlain; he can <hi>mortifie all the dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of he body.</hi> Rom. 8. 13. the ſtrongeſt <hi>members on the Earth,</hi> Col 3. 5. and he can <hi>ſeal you unto the day of Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66016:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
